<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life of the most honourable and vertuous lady the Lady Magdalen Viscountesse Montague written ... by Richard Smith. And now translated into English, by C. F[ursdon]..</title>
            <title>Vita illustrissimae Dominae Magdalenae Montis Acuti in Anglia vicecomitissae. English</title>
            <author>Smith, Richard, 1566-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08095</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22811</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S95235</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">71305180</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 71305180</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183906</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08095)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183906)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2209:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life of the most honourable and vertuous lady the Lady Magdalen Viscountesse Montague written ... by Richard Smith. And now translated into English, by C. F[ursdon]..</title>
                  <title>Vita illustrissimae Dominae Magdalenae Montis Acuti in Anglia vicecomitissae. English</title>
                  <author>Smith, Richard, 1566-1655.</author>
                  <author>Fursdon, Cuthbert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press], Permissu Superiorum,,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[St. Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXVII. [1627].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Headpieces, initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: *⁴ A-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and creased. Text inked out at pp. 22-23. Missing text supplied on typed slip at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
                  <note>Translation of Vita illustrissimae Dominae Magdalenae Montis Acuti in Anglia vicecomitissae.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Montagu, Magdalen Browne, --  viscountess, 1538-1608.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Nobility --  England --  Biography --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:183906:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183906:1"/>
            <p> THE LIFE OF THE MOST HONOVRABLE AND VERTVOVS LADY <hi>THE LA. MAGDALEN</hi> VISCOVNTESSE MONTAGVE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written in Latin, and publiſhed ſoone after her death, By RICHARD SMITH, Doctour of Diuinity, and her Confeſſour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now tranſlated into Engliſh, by C. F.</p>
            <figure/>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mulier timens Dominum, ipſa laudabitur.</hi>
               </p> 
               <bibl>Prou. 3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum, M. DC. XXVII.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:183906:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:183906:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE ANTONY-MARIA, <hi>Viſcount Montague,</hi> My very good Lord, and Mayſter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAVING finiſhed this little Tranſlation, the Authour of the Worke, whoſe Will was to me a Commandment to vndertake the ſame, did alſo enioyne me to addreſſe it to the protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſome worthy Patron; which once reſolued, I made no difficulty of the choyce. For as your Lord.<hi rend="sup">p</hi> may of due iuſtice challeng the whole intereſt of all my actions and labours, this ſubiect in particuler hath moſt proper relation, before any other, vnto your Lordiſhip. For beſides that it containes many paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the lyfe, and to the Honour of your Lo.<hi rend="sup">ps</hi> moſt Worthy, and Honourable Grandfather, ſo neere, and deere vnto your Lordſhip; this
<pb facs="tcp:183906:3"/> Honourable Lady (whoſe Vertuous Lyfe is the ſcope of this treatiſe) though ſhe were not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall authour of your Lord.<hi rend="sup">ps</hi> lyfe, as in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinity deſcending from her; yet did ſhe proue herſelfe a true and tender Mother, and Grandmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (which many euen naturall Parents neglect) in preſeruing both your Lord.<hi rend="sup">p</hi>, and your Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Fathers lyfe: and what her ſincere affection and continuall care, was of your Lord.<hi rend="sup">p</hi> in your tender yeares, none can better teſtify then your Lo.<hi rend="sup">p</hi>. And though your Lo.<hi rend="sup">p</hi> were not nouriſhed with the milke of her breaſts, yet your Lo.<hi rend="sup">p</hi> hath ſucked the true taſt of her Vertues, and made your ſelfe an heyre of her Honourable talents. I hope therfore that your Lord.<hi rend="sup">p</hi>, in regard of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, will fauour and countenance the Worke, &amp; beare with the rudenes of the ſtile, which yet I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume contayneth nothing but Truth: and therein is the more conformable to this Worthy, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Lady, who though exteriourly affected no curioſity, yea prudently ſhunned it; yet contayned in her, the ſincerity of true Vertue &amp; Piety. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech Almighty God, to graunt your Lord.<hi rend="sup">p</hi> all Happines and Proſperity, for your preſent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and eternall Felicity for your future Glory.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lord.<hi rend="sup">ps</hi> most obliged Seruant, <hi>C. F.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:183906:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE OF THE AVTHOR to the deuout Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOSE auncient Fathers (deuout Reader) who by their writings, eyther gaue ornament to the Christian Religion, or defended it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst Heretikes, did alſo accustome to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to writing the liues of ſuch pious women of their ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, as eyther by affinity, or familiarity were conioyned vnto them. Wherof, whoſoeuer hath byn but indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">The cauſe of this Worke.</note> conuerſant in the workes of <hi>S. Hierome, S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, S. Gregory,</hi> or others, cannot be ignorant. For theſe most holy men vnderstood, that therby they did ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy theyr owne deuotion, gaue honest intermiſsion to <note place="margin">We iudg vertues by the mind not by the ſexe.</note> their grauer ſtudies, prayſed God in his Saintes, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally by theſe examples induced others to piety. I imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their proceedings, though in a far meaner degree, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting for the preſent, my writing against our moderne Heretikes, (which alſo by enioyned employments, I was <note place="margin">Hier. de obit. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellae.</note> inforced to interrupt) haue vndertaken to write the lyfe of the right Vertuous Lady <hi>Magdalen,</hi> with whome I familiarly conuerſed many yeares, and was her Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour. <note place="margin">The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of writing.</note> In writing wherof, as I haue endeauoured to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd barbarous language, ſo haue I purpoſely abstayned
<pb facs="tcp:183906:4"/> from the pleaſing veyne of eloquence, &amp; the flouriſhes of Rhetorike. For as the one vſeth to offend the eares of the Reader, and ſometymes to auert him from reading the matter written: ſo the other by ouermuch delighting ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him leſſe attentiue to the matter it ſelfe, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes makes him doubtfull of the truth therof. The beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a chast Matrone ought to be as free from paynting as from vncleannes. Let thoſe be adorned with wordes whoſe lyfe is not adorned with deeds. Our <hi>Magdalen</hi> doth ſo ſhine with Vertues, that ſhe needeth not the ſple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of a pleaſing diſcourſe. Yea rather, as ſhe euer abstai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from painting, &amp; neuer made vſe of a looking-glaſſe: ſo is it requiſite that all vnneceſſary flouriſh of ſpeech be ſhunned in the deſcription of her lyfe. My principall ayme ſhalbe at the truth, that I write nothing, but what <note place="margin">The fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of this writing.</note> my ſelfe haue ſeene, or haue receyued from the mouth of this Lady her ſelfe, or of other witneſses worthy of credit: ſo that with <hi>S. Hierome</hi> writing the lyfe of <hi>S. Paula, I may call IESVS to witnes, and his Saints, &amp; the very Angell who was Guardian, and companion of this admirable Woman, that I ſpeake nothing for fauour, nothing in flattering manner; but what I am to ſay, I ſpeake as a teſtimony, and leſſe then her merits.</hi> And that which may be a great ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to indifferent Readers, what I heere commit to writing, I vttered before a great audience at the fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the Lady <hi>Magdalen,</hi> her familiar acquaintance there preſent; and diuulging it within the ſpace of 19. monthes after her death, if I lye, I may be diſproued by the mouth, eyes, &amp; testimony of all that knew her; and eſpecially of Heretikes, who ſith they could not endure true glory to be attributed vnto her liuing, would leſse
<pb facs="tcp:183906:4"/> permit falſe honour to be fayned on her, dead. Therfore their ſilence in this matter may be an aſſured testimony <note place="margin">That the liue so ſome pious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may be writen.</note> vnto poſterity of the truth of my diſcourſe. But as I feare not calumniators of the truth, ſo do I deſire to ſatisfy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who perhaps thinke that the liues only of ſuch perſons ought to be recorded, whoſe worthy Sanctity me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riteth that they be enrolled in the Catalogue of Saints. From the iudgment of theſe I cannot but diſsent, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, that not only the liues of <hi>S. Paula,</hi> and <hi>S. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cella,</hi> but alſo of <hi>Bleſilla, Fabiola,</hi> and the like are wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <note place="margin">For exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> by that most graue Father. <hi>S. Hierome;</hi> and the life of <hi>S. Monica</hi> by her Sonne <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> whiles he feareth that ſhe was yet detayned in the paines of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. And with good reaſon; for as Gods power doth not only ſhine in the compoſition of the ſunne and moone, but appeareth alſo in the fabrick of the leſſer starres: ſo his heauenly grace doth not only giue a lustre in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of famous Saints, but ſhineth euen in the worth of euery pious perſon. Beſides the ſunne and moone, to haue added alſo starres vnto the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, was not the leaſt increaſe of their ornament; and ſo to record the liues of ſome pious people, wilbe ſome addition to the glory of God <note place="margin">For the honour of God.</note> and of his Church. And as men for the most part do ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther admire then clime the highest mountaynes, who yet by the lownes of little hilles are inuited to aſcend: ſo, more doe commend, then imitate the vertues of famous Saints, who yet with no great difficulty ayme at the pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of leſſe vertuous perſons. And vnto theſe I propoſe a woman, not famous for rudeneſſe of habit, or rigour of diet, or ſeuerity of diſcipline, or abnegation of the <note place="margin">For edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour.</note> world; but one that was humble, chast, meeke, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and pious, neither reſplendent by miracles, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding
<pb facs="tcp:183906:5"/> with vertues: ſo that they who deſpaire to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the admirable ſanctity of <hi>S. Mary Magdalen,</hi> may ſee themſelues capable to attaine the piety of <hi>Magdalen</hi> Viſcounteſſe <hi>Montague.</hi> Neither yet doe I enrole her in the number of Saints, or the Bleſsed: Mine intention is only for the glory of God, &amp; edification of my neyghbour, ſincerely to commend her lyfe to writing; whether ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the opinion of ſanctity, let others iudge. Thus much (deuout Reader) I deſired to premoniſh thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou takest in hand, the reading of the lyfe of our <hi>Magdalen.</hi> Make thou the benefit thereof, and fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:183906:5"/>
            <head>THE LIFE OF THE LADY MAGDALEN VISCOVNTESSE Montague.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the Birth of the La. Magdalen Viſcounteſſe Montague, and her Education vnder her Mother.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE moſt Ho.<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> and Vertuous Lady <hi>Magdalen</hi> Viſcounteſſe <hi>Montague,</hi> was borne in <hi>England,</hi> of moſt Noble &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike parents, at <hi>Naward Castell,</hi> the Manſion-houſe of her Father, ſcituat in the County of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> not far from the borders of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the yeare of <note place="margin">The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the La. Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen.</note> Chriſt 1538. the 20. of Ianuary. Her Father was <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Dacre,</hi> Baron of <hi>Ghiſland,</hi> a man, beſides the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Nobility of his family, of ſuch power and eſtate, as that he poſſeſſed ſeauen Baronyes (which ſcarce any No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man of <hi>England</hi> euer had) and was of eminent autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity <note place="margin">His nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</note> in the North parts of <hi>England,</hi> and both himſelfe and his anceſtors of very famous eſteeme in <hi>England,</hi> in regard of their notable proweſſe in matters of warre, for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fety and honour of their Country. Neither was he of leſſe <note place="margin">His piety.</note>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:183906:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> piety towards God, for when King Henry the VIII. cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Parlament, purpoſed by the voyces of both Houſes to renounce the obedience to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and by an vnheard of Preſident to arrogate vnto himſelfe the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sander. de ſchiſm. l.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 120.</note> of head of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> fearing leaſt the Lord <hi>Dacre</hi> would not only refuſe to aſſent vnto his luſt, but by his example and authority would animate others to the defence of the ancient fayth, he tooke order to haue him called in queſtion for treaſon; wherin notwithſtanding he was eaſily declared innocent. And when afterwards the King told him, that by the conſent of Parlament he was made Head of the Engliſh Church, and demaunded his opinion what he thought therof; ſcoffingly deriding the vanity of the King, he anſwered: <hi>Hereafter then when your Maieſty offendeth, you may abſolue your ſelfe.</hi> Another time when Queene Elizabeth the daughter of Henry, excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her Father, endeauoured vtterly to exterminate Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion out of <hi>England,</hi> the Lord <hi>Dacre</hi> exhorted the Nobility not to giue conſent to ſuch an enormous act, and to certaine of them offered himſelfe and his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for defence of the Catholique Religion. Her Mother was a woman of like Nobility and Piety, the daughter of <hi>N. Talbot</hi> Earle of Shrewsbury; whoſe anceſtors for their <note place="margin">The Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the La. Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen.</note> moſt heroicall victories gotten in <hi>France,</hi> are exceeding famous both in the French &amp; Engliſh Chronicles. And ſo terrible hath the name of <hi>Talbot</hi> byn heretofore vnto the French, that Mothers and nurſes to ſtill their crying chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, accuſtomed to ſay, <hi>Talbot comes.</hi> Of theſe moſt noble anceſtors deſcended the La. Magdalen Montague, which I relate not, as though ſhe did much eſteeme therof, but becauſe, though Nobility do not augment the valour of vertue, yet it doth adde a kind of luſtre, and ornament vnto it, and maketh it to appeare more gracious in the ſight of man. For, as we may ſay with the Poet:
<q>Gratior eſt claro veniens de ſanguine Virtus.</q>
                  <q>Vertue hath more grace, when it deſcends of noble race.</q> For as a pearle is of great price, though it be hidden vnder
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:183906:6"/> the earth, or couered with ordure be trodden vnder foot; or to vſe S. <hi>Hieromes</hi> words: <hi>A Iewell glittereth in loathſome</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epist.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>matter, and the ſplendour of a moſt pure pearle shineth euen in dirt;</hi> yet it is more gracious and delectable, when it is ſet in gold. So vertue is very eſtimable with whatſoeuer ragged pouerty it is ioyned; but where it is veſted with Nobility, as it were with purple, it doth mooue a greater admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and as the Sunne in a cleare day diſperſing the clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, doth far and neere dilate the beames of his light. For as nothing appeareth more pleaſing and beautifull to thoſe that caſt vp their eyes, then the heauens in a cleere night glittering with diuers ſtarres: ſo to vs caſting dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne our ſight, nothing appeareth more gracious, then No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, adorned, and as it were glittering with diuers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of vertue. For Nobility illuſtrated with Vertues, is a heauen ſcituate on earth adorned with ſtarres. Which in theſe times we may auerre to be ſo much the more true, as the coniunction of Vertue with Nobility is more rare. There was a time when Kings, Queenes, and Princes, <note place="margin">Many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kings &amp; Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland in time paſt.</note> men and women in <hi>England,</hi> as they excelled others in dignity, ſo did they endeauour to exceed them in vertue: whence we may find recorded among the Saints, neere twenty Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and as many Queenes, but of Kings children, Princes &amp; noble perſons more then may be nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred. But now (O griefe) our Princes ſaruing from the fayth of their predeceſſors, the Nobility alſo (for the moſt part) degenerate from the piety of their anceſtors. Wherfore this noble woman deſerueth the greater prayſe before God and men, who would not ſtaine her Nobility with vices and impious hereſie, but endeauoured with all her forces to adorne and illuſtrate it with vertues, and the purity of the Catholike fayth, as in the diſcourſe of her life ſhall appeare. Till the thirteenth yeare of her age ſhe had her education in her Fathers houſe, vnder the pious gouernment of her Mother, where although, as well in regard of her youthfull yeares, as by example of her ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and the cuſtome of other Noble Virgins, as alſo by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:183906:7"/> the delight of the paſtime, ſhe might haue bin induced to <note place="margin">She delig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not in hunting.</note> the ſports of hauking and hunting, ſhe notwithſtanding contemning all this pleaſure, made choice by example of the B. Virgin, rather to abide in quiet repoſe at home, then after the manner of prophane <hi>Diana,</hi> by chaſing wilde beaſts and foule, to ſtray in the mountaines and forreſts; &amp; ſo without a teacher ſhe fulfilled the counſaile which S. <hi>Hierome</hi> giueth to Virgins: <hi>Let her neuer goe forth, leaſt thoſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Laet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>who wander about the citty do find her, least they ſtrike, and wound her, and bereaue her of the veyle of her chaſtity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of her Education, vnder the Counteſſe of</hi> Bedford.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>VVHen ſhe was now thirteene yeares of age, ſhe was by her Father commended to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of <hi>Bedford,</hi> to be educated vnder the prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t diſcipline of that Catholique and Religious Lady. Of whome ſhe accuſtomed to make this relation, which for the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of other women, I thought very requiſite to commit <note place="margin">A barren woman immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> to writing. Wheras ſhe was barren, &amp; had a vehement de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to haue a child, ſhe for a long tyme both by her ſelfe &amp; others beſought Almighty God to vouchſafe to graunt her a ſonne. But as Chriſt ſayd to his diſciples, <hi>Neſcitis quid petatis,</hi> yee know not what yee aske; &amp; as <hi>S. Augustine</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, God ſometymes in anger granteth our petition: ſo this pious woman by the ill euent experienced, that ſhe knew not what ſhe asked, and inſteed of a benefit, requeſted a puniſhment of God. For ſhe brought forth a <note place="margin">She is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by them.</note> ſonne, but ſuch a one, as not only fell into hereſy, which ſhe did extremely abhorre, but did oftentimes ſo impiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly behaue himſelf towards his Mother, as that ſhe would ſometymes with exceeding griefe and teares publikely confeſſe, that ſhe grieuouſly offended God, when deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a ſonne, ſhe had not added this condition, If it might be for his glory, and her comfort; and therfore (ſayd ſhe) I am iuſtly puniſhed by the thing I immoderatly deſyred.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:183906:7"/> Which may be a document to pious parents, that ſterility is not alwayes to be eſteemed as a puniſhment inflicted of God, nor that children are alwayes to be reputed as a gift, and teſtimony of diuine fauour; and that they ſhould demaund no temporall thing of God, but as far forth as his diuine prouidence foreſeeth it to be agreable to his pleaſure, and profitable for them. But let vs returne to the La. Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tague. She liued three yeares vnder the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe, whome ſhe ſo diligently attended, that ſhe did not only performe the office of her gentlewoman, but in the abſence of her chamber-mayd, diſcharged her ſeruice al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, being ready euery houre of the night whenſoeuer the Counteſſe called (which by reaſon of her old age and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities ſhe often did) to riſe out of her bed, and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to attend her. Yea the right Noble Virgin being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately educated, did not diſdaine, of her owne accord, and vnknowne to the Counteſſe, to performe that baſe kind of ſeruice, which curious eares refuſe to heare related. So much had God preuented her with his benedictions, and <note place="margin">Her rare humility and duty.</note> had indued her with ſuch humility, euen in that age, wherein, as being the flower of youth, women are ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily puffed vp in pride and inſolencie. And this act ſhe ſometimes accuſtomed to relate to her Grand-children without bluſhing, yea with a kind of complacence, by ſuch example to exhort them to humility.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of her liuing at the Court, vnder</hi> Queene Mary, <hi>and of her Marriage vnto the Viſcount Montague.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>VVHen in this manner ſhe had ſpent three yeares in all vertue and piety, vnder the diſcipline of the Counteſſe of <hi>Bedford,</hi> it happened that <hi>K. Edward</hi> the ſixt being dead (whoſe childhood certaine impious men abuſed to ouerthrow Catholike Religion in England) Queene Mary, not without euident miracle, &amp; the great
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:183906:8"/> benignity of God, againſt all power and policy of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, obtayned the Kingdome of England; and expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling perfidious hereſy, reſtabliſhed the auncient and true Religion. She admitted <hi>Magdalen</hi> to the Court, and to <note place="margin">She is Maid of honour to Q Mary.</note> the number of her noble wayting-women (who are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually called Ladyes of Honour) where her vertue and virginall modeſty got, not only more ample place to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate it ſelfe, but alſo found greater occaſion and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xample of progreſſe and increaſe. For at that tyme the Court of <hi>England</hi> was a ſchoole of vertue, a nurſery of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, a manſion of piety. The Queene her ſelfe did ſhine <note place="margin">What the Court of England vvas vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Q Mary.</note> as the Moone in all kind of vertue, whoſe prayſes all hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories doe record. Her Ladyes and women did glitter as the ſtarres; and what ſhining ſtarres they were, the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may coniecture by what I will relate of one of them from the mouth of the La. <hi>Magdalen.</hi> She accuſtomed to ariſe from her bed very early, and attyring her ſelfe with all poſſible ſpeed, haſtened to the Chappell, where knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt a wall, and the other part of her face couered with her head attyre, ſhe accuſtomed to ſpend certayne houres in deuout prayer, and to ſhed abundance of teares before Almighty God. And yet withall, would ſhe not be any tyme abſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any office of piety preſcribed to her, &amp; her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions. Neyther was ſhe content in this ſort to ſpend the day, but aroſe from her bed in the night, and proſtrate on the ground applyed her ſelf to prayer a good part of the night. Which, when the La. <hi>Magdalen</hi> had once perceyued, ſhe finding her deuotion to be diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, no otherwiſe then if ſhe had byn apprehended in <note place="margin">Rare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion of of one of the may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</note> ſome notorious Iewd fault, falling on her knees, with many teares ſhe beſought her for the honour of God, that ſhe would not bewray her ſecret exerciſes of piety to any creature whiles ſhe liued. O humble, O truly pious vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and truly a Mayd (as ſhe was called) of Honour! for ſhe was a mayd of Honeſty, of Purity, and of Piety. O happy Court with ſuch Courtyers! and happy England with ſuch a Court, which for vertuous lyfe, gaue not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:183906:8"/> place to many Cloyſters, &amp; whence, as from a fountain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, examples of piety did flow into all Prouinces of England! Would to God this purity had continued in our Virgin Courtiers, and the Mother therof, the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion, had ſtill floriſhed; then had not the Court of England byn ſpotted with the notorious infamy of laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuiouſnes, as ſoone after it was. But that I may expreſſe my griefe in this cauſe, I deſire my Countrymen to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the notable purity of the maydes of Honour vnder Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> and the infamous reproches which ſome <note place="margin">The dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the Court vnder a Catholike and an hereticall Queene.</note> of them haue incurred vnder Q. <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> and they will find what difference there is betweene a moſt chaſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and a moſt impure Hereſy. Vnder ſuch a worthy Queene, and with ſuch Companions the La. <hi>Magdalen</hi> being educated, ſhe had ſcarce liued two yeares in the Court, but that the rare vertues, and ornaments both of her body and her ſoule, drew the hartes of many princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Courtyers to affect her. Among whome, two eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at one tyme did earneſtly ſeeke her in the way of <note place="margin">Diuers deſire to marry the La. Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen.</note> mariage. The one was <hi>Syr Iohn Arundell</hi> knight, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly (for his great wealth &amp; authority) called the <hi>Great;</hi> who afterward vnder <hi>Q. Elizabeth,</hi> ſuffering long impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Catholike Fayth, dyed a glorious Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour. He was ſo enflamed with chaſt affection towardes this Lady, that he would neuer deſiſt to ſollicite her, till he vnderſtood that her Eſpouſalls with another were pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. Then hauing loſt his hope, though not his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, he came to her, and congratulating her eſpouſalls, wiſhed her the moſt fortunate and happy mariage that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer woman had. The other was <hi>Antony,</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Montague,</hi> the iſſue of the moſt famous Marqueſſe <hi>Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue</hi> (who deſcended both of the houſe of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> and of the moſt auncient Nobility of <hi>England)</hi> one of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy Councell of the Queene, and knight of the moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Order of the garter. This Nobleman, before he ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his deſire vnto the La. <hi>Magdalen,</hi> ſought by letters, the conſent of the Queene, who with no ſmall commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:183906:9"/> of her Mayd, wrote him this anſwere: <hi>Hauing conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The letter of Queene Mary.</note> 
                  <hi>her perſon, her vertuous report, birth, great number of friends and other benefits which this Alliance will bring vnto you, with other like motiues, which I perceiue you prudently ponder, I confeſse that I ſo fauour this matter, as I do not only giue free conſent, that you treat with her therof, but alſo, ſo fit do I esteeme this match to ech of you, that with my hart I wish it a happy concluſion; &amp; shall exceedingly ioy, that you haue found ſo conuenient a wife, and she ſo fortunate a condition.</hi> The moſt Ho.<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> Viſcount hauing in this ſort obtayned firſt the conſent of the Queene, &amp; then of the Lady, of her Parents, and friends, marryed her in <note place="margin">She is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to the Viſcount Montague</note> London at the Kinges houſe called S. <hi>Iames,</hi> the Queene her ſelfe with a great traine of the Nobility being preſent. This then was that <hi>Iſaac,</hi> whome God prepared for this moſt chaſt <hi>Rebecca,</hi> of whoſe heroicall Vertues, I will briefly note ſome few, which I receiued from this Ladies mouth, becauſe they giue ſome light to the relating of her Piety.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the worthy Vertues of the Viſcount Montague, husband of the La. Magdalen.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>THe firſt Vertue that occurreth to be related of this <note place="margin">A rare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection vnto cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity in the Viſcount.</note> Noble man, is his rare affection vnto chaſtity. For when (his Mother being dead) his Father kept a Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine, as ſoone as this yong Gent. vnderſtood therof, he went alone to his Father, and on his knees beſought him to leaue that courſe of life, ſo hatefull vnto God, damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his ſoule, and diſhonorable to all his friends; and to take to wife ſome honeſt Gentlewoman, with whome he might liue honourably before men, and in the fauour of God. To whome his Father ſmyling, ſayd: Thou doeſt giue me ſuch counſayle, Sonne, as will be thirty thouſand pounds out of thy way. But the pious youth anſwered, that he nothing regarded that loſſe, whereby
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:183906:9"/> he might gaine his Fathers ſoule and reputation. And ſo much did the pious admonition of the Sonne preuaile with the Father, that diſmiſſing his Concubine, he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed a wife, with whome he ſpent the reſt of his life ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly. And the Sonne in this one act ſhewed great piety towards his Father, religion towards God, and with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of riches an admirable loue of chaſtity, euen at that time when, hereſie being newly crept into <hi>England,</hi> in a manner all the youth was corrupted with all kind of laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuious liberty. Neither was this a ſparkle, which after a litle blaze is ſodenly extinguiſhed, but a true flame of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection vnto chaſtity, and a firme purpoſe rather to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard his life, then his chaſtity. For when afterward he was Embaſſadour in Spayne, and was fallen into a moſt perillous and moleſtfull diſeaſe, and the Phiſitians gaue iudgement, that he could not recouer, vnleſſe he had the company of a woman; and at that time there lying dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly ouer againſt his lodgings a moſt beautifull Engliſh queane, who by all laſciuious allurements endeauoured to induce him to lewdnes; notwithſtanding, neither by the Counſaile of the Phiſitians, nor the perſwaſion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <note place="margin">He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth Chaſtity before his life.</note> nor the wanton allurements of the queane, nor the loue of his life could he be moued, to preferre the health of his body before the ſafety of his ſoule, or the loue of his life before his charity vnto God; but vtterly reiecting all lewd Counſaile, he was neuer quiet till he had baniſhed the queane out of thoſe lodgings. O holy man! O chaſt <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> whome neyther the pleaſure of ſinne, nor the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity and ſecreſie of the fact, nor the hope of health, nor the feare of death could induce to incurre the loſſe of his chaſtity, to violate his fayth plighted to his wife, or to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend God. And albeit, being ſhortly after by the Queene recalled into his Country, he recouered of this diſeaſe, who yet would not eſteeme him equall, or very like to B. <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> and other moſt holy men, who choſe rather to looſe their liues, then to abuſe their bodies inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently? And this his worthy chaſtity was accompanied
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:183906:10"/> with equall, or rather greater loue of Gods worſhip and Religion. For when K. <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt (or rather others in his name) aboliſhing the religion of his predeceſſors, as an other <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> had erected a new Altar, and ſet vp gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den calues (I meane a new worſhip, or rather ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) and almoſt all people, either for affectation of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelty, or for feare of puniſhment flocked to that new and enormous ſuperſtition, this pious youth would not ſtaine himſelfe with ſuch haynous crime; but like an other <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bias</hi> ſought out the ſeruice of God, practiſed by his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and both deuoutly, and publikly, and with due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence frequented the ſame. For which matter being <note place="margin">He is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to priſon for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God.</note> committed to priſon, he was ſo far from being deiected therewith, that adorning his chamber with tapiſtry, he therby gaue his perſecutors aſſurance, that his purpoſe was, rather with <hi>Daniell</hi> to liue in priſon, then to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from the diuine ſeruice of his God. Neither did he alone ſo conſtantly imbrace the Catholike Religion, but did alſo animate others to the like conſtancy. For when his Father by the impious aduiſe of ſome others, for to auoyd the offence of Heretikes, was perſwaded to abſent himſelfe from the Parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that day when vnder <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt it was conſulted of changing Religion; when the vertuous yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Gent. vnderſtood therof, he neuer deſiſted till by prayers, teares, and ſuch other reaſons as he could, he had wrought his Father to go to the Parlament, and couragiouſly to giue his voyce for the true Religion. And when afterward vnder <hi>Q. Mary</hi> the true Religion did floriſh againe, none was more ſtudious then he to adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the Catholike fayth. For which his zeale, and other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues worthy of ſuch imployment, he eſpecially was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen <note place="margin">He is ſent Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour to the Pope.</note> of that Queene to goe Embaſſadour to the Pope, and deſiring pardon of the ſchiſme paſt, to promiſe future obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in the name of the whole kingdome. Which he performed to his exceeding prayſe, the honour of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the glory of God, and the applauſe of the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> world. But when a few yeares after (with grieſe be it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:183906:10"/> ſpoken) by commaundement of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> there <note place="margin">He exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Nobility to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like fayth</note> was conſultation agayne among the Nobility of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme for ſuppreſſing the Catholike Fayth, this moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Viſcount, making a graue, eloquent, and pithy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, exhorted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to permit themſelues to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed away with euery wind of new doctrine, nor to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue that, which themſelues ſo very lately had ratifyed, and with ſolemne ceremony had promiſed inuiolably to obſerue; nor to aboliſh that Religion, wherein all their Chriſtian anceſtors liued with ſuch ſplendour, and dyed with ſuch piety, to imbrace that which a ſmall number, &amp; they baſe, voluptuous, turbulent men of no reputation, &amp; diſagreeing among themſelues, had inuented, and which had neuer ſet foot in England, had not in famous luſt, and greedines of Church-goods depraued K. <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. But when he perceiued the principall of the Nobility of the realme, partly being deluded with the vaine hope of marrying the Q. partly blinded with the couetous deſire of earthly riches, not to admit good Counſaile, but like the deafe aſpe to ſtop their eares (as the Pſalmiſt ſayth) at whatſoeuer voyces ſweetly enchaunting, what he could not perſwade others, himſelfe conſtantly maintayned, &amp; obſerued. And if ſomtime afterward he went to hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Churches, it was not ſo much to be imputed to him, as to his Prieſt, a learned and piousman indeed, but too fearfull, who ſuppoſing it expedient ſomething to giue to the tyme, durſt not determine ſuch a fact to be ſinne. For when that Prieſt being dead, he had entertayned an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, who with Prieſtly courage told him that it was a grieuous offence and hatefull to God and the Church, &amp; pernicious to his ſoule, to be preſent at hereticall ſeruice, he was ſo far from defending his fact, that (as I receiued from the mouth of one that was preſent) inſtantly put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his hat, &amp; falling on his knees, both with geſture of his whole body, &amp; with his tongue, he moſt humbly ſubmitted himſelf to the cenſure of the catholike Church, and piouſly promiſed neuer thence forward to be preſent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:183906:11"/> at hereticall ſeruice, which all the reſt of his lyfe he exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerued. Many other notable things might be rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of this right Nobleman, but that mine intended ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect calleth me another way, and therfore I will adde only one thing, that the Reader may vnderſtand in what pious manner this worthy man ended his holy lyfe. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it pleaſed God to purge the ruſt of his ſinnes in this lyfe, he permitted him to fall into a tedious, troubleſome, and lingring kind of infirmity, wherof he dyed. Which in the opinion of many, happening vnto him by witch-craft, (from which opinion himſelfe ſeemed not to diſſent) though certayne Sorcerers promiſed to reſtore him to his former health, if he would but giue way therto; he not only refuſed to conſent to their iniquity, but deteſting all helpes of the ſlaues of Sathan, ſeuerely forbad his friends euer to vſe ſuch deteſtable remedyes, for the recouery of his health. And ſo declaring, not only in words with the Pſalmiſt, but euen in deeds: <hi>Meliorem ſibi miſericordiam</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.</note> 
                  <hi>Dei eſſe ſuper vitas, That Gods mercy was better to him then lyfe,</hi> being by a long triall purged, he piouſly ended his lyfe in our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the mutuall loue betweene the La.</hi> Magdalen, <hi>and her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; of her iſsue, and of her rare Charity towards her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands children.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>BY the aforeſayd piety of the Viſcount, it wilbe eaſy for the Reader to make a coniecture of the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of his Lady, who being of her owne nature and <note place="margin">The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding loue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvveene the La. Mag. and her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</note> education addicted vnto piety, by the further iuduceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of her husbands example, more ſpeedily ran the courſe of vertue. They liued together in great loue and amity 36. yeares: and whiles I was writing this, I lighted by chance on a letter of D. <hi>Langdales,</hi> who was for many yeares theyr Confeſſor, wherein, in teſtimony of theyr loue and piety he thus ſpeaketh vnto them: <hi>Fare yee well,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:183906:11"/> 
                  <hi>moſt louing couple, of one mind, of one loue, &amp; (which is rare in this world) of one piety.</hi> She (as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> left written of S. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Confeſs. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Monica) being ioyned to a husband, ſerued him as her Lord; and God made her beautifull, and reuerently amiable, and admirable to her husband.</hi> Her husband had by her eight children, <hi>Syr George</hi> Browne, &amp; <hi>Syr Henry</hi> Browne honourable knights, and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> wife to the Lord <hi>Dormer;</hi> of whoſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <note place="margin">The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the La. Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len.</note> becauſe they yet lyue (according the Counſayle of the wiſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) I wilbe ſilent; the reſidue dyed eyther infants or vnmaryed, leauing no iſſue, excepting <hi>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. Iane</hi> Browne moſt like her mother in vertue, maryed to <hi>Francis Lacon</hi> Eſquire, to whome ſhe brought forth many children. And <note place="margin">Fateor nulla ſic amabat liberos. Hier, de Sancta Paula.</note> albeyt the La. <hi>Magdalen</hi> moſt tenderly loued her children and (what ſhe could without iniury to others) careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aymed at their preferment; yet her husband hauing by a former wyfe one only Sonne, of exceeding tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and infirme, who only was to precede her Sons in his Fathers in heritance, ſhe had neuertheles ſo ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous a care of his health, as if he had byn her owne child. Yea his Sonne, the preſent moſt Honourable Viſcount <note place="margin">Her vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards her ſonne in-lavv.</note> 
                  <hi>Montague,</hi> both by words (as I vnderſtand) and by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings (as we ſhall hereafter recite) imputeth the benefit of his owne, and his Fathers lyfe to the rare piety of this Mother-in-law, which is alſo confimed by the teſtimony of others. And when alſo, by an offence which her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band conceyued, occaſion was preſented whereby ſhe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Infrac.</hi> 16.</note> might exceedingly haue rayſed the fortunes of her owne children, ſhe was ſo far from making vſe thereof, to the <note place="margin">She pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth the life of her ſonne-in lavv, and of his ſonne.</note> iniury of her Sonne-in-law his child, that ſhe paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed her husband, and reduced him into fauour. So much did eyther the loue of her husband, whome ſhe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in all his children, or the ingrafted Nobility of mind, or finally the loue of God, and equity preuayle with her. In which proceeding ſhe ſhewed a worthy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xample to all Mothers-in-law; and ſo much therfore did ſhe purchaſe the loue of the preſent Viſcount, that none of her owne children exceeded him in filiall affection.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:183906:12"/> And though, at the tyme that her husband dyed, ſhe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the iudgement of many, to be neerer death her ſelfe; yet ſo much force did loue adde vnto her, that ariſing out of her bed, ſhe held him in her armes whiles he yielded vp his laſt breath. And as S. <hi>Hierome</hi> writeth of the moſt noble widdow S. <hi>Paula: She ſo bewayled him, as if she would haue dyed with him; she ſo betooke her ſelfe to the ſeruice of God, as she ſeemed to haue wished his death.</hi> For wheras for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly obliged to wedlock, ſhe was conſtrayned to think <note place="margin">Her pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and gratitude tovvards her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed.</note> (as the Apoſtle ſayth) <hi>how alſo to pleaſe her husband,</hi> now that band being diſſolued, and hauing gotten a more ſetled freedome of exerciſing her vertue, ſhe applied herſelfe more attentiuely to the ſeruice of God. Neither yet did ſhe neglect the care of her husbands ſoule, for whome ſhe twice euery weeke cauſed Maſſe to be ſayd, and herſelfe ſayd the office of the dead; euery yeare ſhe procured a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Aniuerſary on the day of his departure, &amp; moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently when ſhe tooke her repaſt, and often at other ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, euen to the laſt day of her life, ſhe was moſt grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully mindfull of him, vſing theſe, or the like words: <hi>God be mercifull to his ſoule who left me this.</hi> But now leauing her husband let vs come to her vertues. Wherof before I begin to ſpeake, this I muſt profeſſe, that I neither know them all, nor can I according to their worth expreſſe any one of them. For if the moſt eloquent Father <hi>S. Hierome</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that <hi>although all his members were conuerted into to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gues, &amp; all his ioynts did ſound with humane voyce, yet could he deliuer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worthy the vertues of S. Paula:</hi> What may I hope for, <note place="margin">In vita S. Paulae.</note> who am not worthy to carry the bookes of <hi>S. Hierome,</hi> &amp; yet am to write the life of that widdow, who as ſhe did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall <hi>S. Paula</hi> in Nobility, ſo did ſhe imitate her in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. I will therfore partly imitate thoſe painters, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to deſcribe ſome Army on a tablet, do draw the iuſt proportion of ſome few ſoldiers, but of the reſidue they make appeare only their heades, or the vpper part of their helmets, or the points of their ſpeares, wherby they inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the number of the ſoldiers to be great, which they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:183906:12"/> can rather propoſe to the vnderſtanding of the beholders, then exhibite to their eyes. Thus I ſee I muſt endeauour in writing the lyfe of this pious Lady, that I may deſcribe ſome few of her vertues moſt apparent vnto me, but the reſt I muſt leaue to be conceyued in the ſecret iudgment of the Reader. Although euen in this I ſhall eaſily find the Penſill of the Painter more fortunate then my Pen, for he can draw the iuſt ſtature and true proportion of all the members, at leaſt of ſome of the ſoldiers; wheras my Pen cannot fully and entirely deſcribe any one vertue of this pious Lady. Which that I ſpeak without amplificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is apparent to all that knew her, and the prudent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may eaſily conceaue as much, by what I am to relate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the excellent Humility of the La.</hi> Magdalen.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe, as the moſt graue Doctour of the Church <hi>S. Hierome</hi> writeth in the lyfe of S. <hi>Paula: The first, or chiefe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In act ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 30.</note> 
                  <hi>vertue of a Chriſtian is Humility.</hi> And as <hi>S. Chryſostome</hi> ſayth; <hi>It is the Roote, Mother, and Nurſe, the ſupport, and bound of all good things;</hi> therfore being to write the vertues of this pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous woman, let vs beginne with her Humility. That ſhe was eminent heerein, is apparent by her ſpeach, her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, <note place="margin">Her hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility in ſpeach.</note> attire, and acts. For her ſpeach was mild and peaceable, and free from all contention, and more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to giue way to, then to contend euen with her infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours. Neyther did ſhe diſdaine to ſpeake vnto any, yea <note place="margin">In her conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> when ſhe walked abroad, ſhe ſometymes tooke occaſion of diſcourſe with ſuch poore people as ſhe caſually met with all, and ſometymes went to their houſes, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly diſcourſed with them of their affayres. She ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not the conuerſation of any honeſt perſon, yea ſhe <note place="margin">In her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell.</note> viſited the poore, therby to get them the more eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among their neighbours. Her attyre, after the death of her husband, when ſhe was not bound to pleaſe the eyes of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:183906:13"/> any man, was ſuch, that as S. <hi>Hierome</hi> writeth of <hi>S. Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la: Who had not knowne her, would not take her to be who she was, but to be the meaneſt of the hand-mayds.</hi> On working dayes, ſhe had her head dreſſed with plaine linnen, couered with an ordinary Hat, vſed in <hi>England</hi> commonly, by ſeruing-Maydes. But on Feaſts (in honour of the Dayes) ſhe put on a French-hood. Her gowne in Summer was of ſay, in winter of Cotton, on which, to keep her ſhoulders from cold, ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly wore a courſe Iriſh mantle. She neuer wore knit ſtockings, either of ſilke, worſted, &amp; wolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but <note place="margin">She neuer adorned her ſelfe by a glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe.</note> only and altogether of Kerſie. Her ſmock was of rude &amp; courſe linnen, ſuch as noble women would eſteeme a pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to weare. She neuer in her life dreſſed her head, or adorned her ſelfe by a glaſſe, which in a woman, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Noble, and a Courtier, may be eſteemed as a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, ſith women otherwiſe deuout, haue byn ſubiect to this defect. In ſo much, as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> writeth of <hi>Bleſilla; That she looked all the day in a glaſſe, to ſee what she wanted.</hi> For what do women more anxiouſly ayme at, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to adorne their face, who, <hi>dum moliuntur</hi> (as he ſayd) <hi>dum comuntur, dum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">In vita Paulae.</note> 
                  <hi>pectuntur, annus eſt.</hi> A yeare doth but ſuffice to adorne, attire &amp; beautify themſelues. And wherof ſhould that woman be proud, who neglects her face? That it may be leſſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable, that our <hi>Magdalen</hi> was free from that imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, wherunto euen S. <hi>Paula</hi> in her youth was ſubiect, by the confeſſion of S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> to wit, of painting her face with cheeke verniſh, ceruſe, or other like colourings. For her endeauour was to adorne her ſoule with vertues, and the glaſſe wherin ſhe daily beheld the ſame, was her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as by that which we ſhall heereafter relate, ſhall more clearly appeare. And that we may ſpeake a litle of <note place="margin">Her acts of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</note> the actes of her humility, what I pray you, was that which we formerly mentioned, when in her tender youth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, &amp; vnknowne to her Lady, ſhe freely performed ſuch a baſe office? What was that other act, which ſhe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently exerciſed, as to be preſent at the trauell of diuers meane, and poore women, and her ſelfe girded with an
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:183906:13"/> apron diligently to aſſiſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Theſe certainly were wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and euident teſtimonies of profound humility; yet of all the reſt is this moſt excellent, knowne only to my ſelfe. Wheras ſhe had made choyce to vſe me in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Confeſſion, I aduiſed her of a certaine methode of diſcuſſing her conſcience, more conuenient for her (in mine opinion) then that ſhe had formerly vſed. Wherein I did perhaps ſo imperfectly expreſſe my meaning, that the pious Lady vnderſtood me to ſuſpect, that ſhe did not ſincerely diſcouer her ſinnes, but did conceale ſomething requiſite to be opened. And what (thinke you) did this Lady, no leſſe emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Eſtate then in Nobility, ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touched (as to her ſeemed) in her honour, and ſo iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly condemned (as ſhe conceiued) of ſo hainous a crime as is ſacriledge, and the abuſe of almighty God in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? and this by him whome ſhe ſo much eſteemed, as before any other ſhe choſe him for guide &amp; Paſtour of her ſoule? What did ſhe I ſay? did ſhe by countenance, word, act, or geſture diſcouer any ſigne of offence? Yea, did ſhe excuſe her ſelfe, or aske what moued me to giue ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous a cenſure of her? None of all theſe; but making moſt humble reuerence, departed, and ſo remayned a whole weeke, ſhewing in all that time no token of diſpleaſure. But yet, when almighty God had by this meanes tryed <note place="margin">A rare humility in ſecret.</note> the humility, and patience of his ſeruant, therby perhaps to let me know what an humble ſoule he had committed to my care, he ſuggeſted vnto her in her next confeſſion to aske me, for what cauſe I ſuſpected that ſhe had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed ſomething in confeſſion, more fearing my iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then relying on her owne innocency, and doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that I did perceyue ſomething, which ſhe ſaw not in her ſelfe. O ſubmiſſiue humility! O profound reſignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſoule of this great Lady! And truly great, becauſe in her owne eyes ſhe was ſo little. Some Penitents per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps would haue taken it grieuouſly, to haue byn que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned of ſuch leſſer faultes whereof their conſciences ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed them; others would take it offenſiuely, to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:183906:14"/> of thoſe crimes, wherof there might be iuſt ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion that they were guilty; but this humble and truly penitent woman, was content not only to be examined of her ſinnes (yea this ſhe very much deſired) but euen (as ſhe conceyued) to be condemned, not of ſome ſleight de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but of a moſt grieuous cryme; and out of her humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, more feared the iudgment of her Confeſſour, then confided in the teſtimony of her owne conſcience. And therfore if according to the greatnes of her Humility, we will meaſure the worth of her other vertues, (as he did who by the foot-ſtep of <hi>Hercules</hi> aymed at his whole ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) we may without any other argument collect, that the rare ſubmiſſion of this ſoule was conſequently accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyed with many excellent vertues. For where God layd ſo ſolid a foundation of humility, out of all doubt he built a notable edifice of vertue. For where there is much Humility, there is much Sanctity. Whence the moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Mother of Chriſt, and his Precurſor, as they exceeded all other in humility, ſo did they precede them in ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Of this her Humility then it proceeded, that ſhe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <note place="margin">An hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſaying and deed.</note> accuſtomed to ſay, that ſhe was a ſack of dung; and when in her laſt ſicknes her drinke did once diſpleaſe her, ſodenly reprehending her ſelfe, and bitterly wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, ſhe ſayd: <hi>Why should I miſlike my drink for whome any drink is too good?</hi> And ſhe at length had gotten ſo perfect a victory ouer Pride, that a litle before her death, with great confidence in God, &amp; conſolation of mind, ſhe told <note place="margin">She triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer pride.</note> me, that thence forward ſhe feared not pryde. O happy woman, who in earth cold triumph ouer that vice which threw the higheſt Cherubims downe from the higheſt place of heauen, and caſt our firſt parents out of Paradiſe, and then which, Piety hath not a more capitall enemy! For as it is moſt difficult to ſuppreſſe a flame; ſo is it hard not to glory when one hath done any thing worthy of prayſe. How highly then hath God now eleuated this woman, who promiſed to exalt the humble? and how iuſtly might ſhe chalenge a place of the lapſed Angells,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:183906:14"/> who by humility aſcended thither, whence they by pride did fall?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Of her notable Chaſtity.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>THE next vertue of this pious woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof we are to ſpeake, is her Chaſtity. This in both ſexes is moſt precious; for as the Scripture witneſſeth, <hi>There is no ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſiaſt. c.</hi> 29.</note> 
                  <hi>worthy eſteeme of a continent ſoule:</hi> Yet doth it eſpecially ſhine in women, as the principall flower in their garla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſo that the ſame ſcripture ſayth: <hi>Gratia ſuper gratiam, mulier</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 26.</note> 
                  <hi>ſancta &amp; pudorata.</hi> But a woman wanting this vertue, <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam stercusin via conculcabitur,</hi> as the ſame ſcripture ſayth. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 9.</note> But this womans Chaſtity did equall her humility, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the tyme of her virginity, of her wedlocke, and of her widdowhood, ſhe gaue euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teſtimonies. For whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſhe liued a mayd of honour in the Court, on a tyme King <hi>Philip</hi> who had maryed Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> youthful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opened a window, where by chance ſhe was wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing her face, and ſportingly putting in his arme, which ſome other would perhaps haue taken as a great honour, and reioyced therat, ſhe knowing that the condition of virgins was not vnlike vnto flowers, which with the leaſt touch doe looſe of their beauty, hauing more regard of her owne purity, then of the Kings Maieſty, ſhe tooke <note place="margin">She ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth the Kings ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</note> a ſtaffe lying by, and ſtrongly ſtroke the King on the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Which fact the prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t King did not only take with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence, but it was the increaſe of her honour and eſteeme. And in what manner, thinke you, would ſhe haue diſdayned any other, who ſo reiected the King? or what would ſhe not haue done againſt the King, attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any lewdnes, who ſo entertayned him ieſting? When ſhe was marryed, ſhe ſo carryed her ſelfe, that as <hi>S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> writeth of <hi>S. Paula: She was an example to all Matrones, &amp; ſo behaued herſelfe, that the tongues euen of ill ſpeakers neuer durſt forge any ill of her.</hi> For who could ſpeake any diſhoneſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:183906:15"/> thing of her? who euer heard impute ſpeach of her mouth? who could charge her with any wanton caſt of her eye? who could diſcouer in her any vnchaſt affection? Yet did ſhe not want occaſions of incontinencie, whiles her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand was thrice out of <hi>England,</hi> nor did there want lewd ſollicitors, euen of the chiefeſt ranck of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe when ſhe perceiued to tend thereunto, ſhe with a certaine pious indignation ſo reiected them, that they durſt not twice attempt the ſame. And this her chaſtity was ſo perſpicuous, and well knowne, that it ſo repreſſed the inclinations, and brideled the tongues euen of ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meles <note place="margin">She brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſhameles perſons.</note> perſons, as that they were aſhamed to attempt, or vtter any lewd matter in her preſence. And albeit ſhe choſe not the higheſt degree of Chaſtity, which is Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; that, perhaps may rather be aſcribed to want of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe and counſaile (wherof ſhe often lamented to haue bin deſtitute in her youth) then of deſire to follow the beſt. For when, being 18. yeares of age, and newly marryed, her husband was ſent to that famous ſeige of S. <hi>Quintius,</hi> ſhe made a firme reſolution, if he ſhould dye, neuer to know any other man: ſo that we may iudge of her, as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> writeth of S. <hi>Paula: Hauing once entred Matrimonie, she neuer thought of other thing day or night, but, the fruit of marriage being rendred, how to attaine the ſecond degree of chastity.</hi> For her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band being dead, the Lord <hi>Cobham,</hi> a man of great eſtate, honour, and authority in the realme, did moſt earneſtly <note place="margin">She refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</note> ſeeke her in mariage, and offered her a very fayre dowry, but ſhe gaue him ſo reſolute a denyall, that thence forward ſhe was no more ſollicited by ſutors. This example is not ordinary in <hi>England,</hi> in this ſo corrupt an age, where ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times women of honour, after the death of their husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, not finding others equall to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in dignity, do mary euen their ſeruants, or men of meane condition. In this manner liued this Hon.<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> Lady all her life, <hi>without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion</hi> (as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>in the middeſt of a crooked and peruerſe Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, among whome she shined as light in the world.</hi> And <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.</note> albeit theſe be arguments of rare chaſtity, yet I will adde
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:183906:15"/> one far more ſingular &amp; eminent, the truth wherof though it depend on her only teſtimony, yet ſith God doth <hi>deuide to euery one</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſayth) <hi>according as he will,</hi> &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.</note> greater guiftes vnto his ſeruants; and ſhe being ſo worthy a Lady, as whoſoeuer knew her, could haue no ſuſpition that for vaine glory ſhe would delude her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, I litle feare, but that it will find credit with the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall Reader; &amp; this it was: that in all her life ſhe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <note place="margin">The La. Mag ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer felt the rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion of the fleſh.</note> felt the inuoluntary ſtings, or (as they call it) rebellion of the fleſh, wherby her mind ſhould be prouoked to luſt. O ſingular chaſtity! O what kind of taſt of the ſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie! O wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull arguments of Gods loue towards this woman! For with what purity did God beautify her ſoule, who ſo adorned her fleſh? what treaſure did he lay vp in ſo rich a cheſt? what pure Tabernacle of the holy Ghoſt was that ſoule, which inhabited ſo pure and chaſt a body? Neither yet is this all, that in this kind I can relate of this chaſt woman, but as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> ſayth of himſelfe writing the life of <hi>S. Paula: I am conſtrayned to omit many things, least I should exceed the beliefe of things, and by detractors be reputed a lyer.</hi> But what chaſt ſoule, thinke you, had ſhe, who was freed from that interiour, and cruell enemie of her chaſtity? And if ſome time the enemie did ſuggeſt that vnto her ſoule, whereto her fleſh did not allure her; if ſhe were waking, ſhe did inſtantly not only reiect it from her mind, but euen with ſpitting, or ſome exteriour ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne, did declare how much ſhe deteſted it. But if it happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in her ſleep, when reaſon had not power to giue her aſſiſtance, yet did her body ſo ſtriue and labour to expell that filthy ſuggeſtion, that it awakened her mind, after which the victory was eaſy. O happy woman, whoſe very fleſh (in which, euen in holy men, as the Prophet <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal;</hi> 7.</note> ſpeaketh) <hi>there is no ſoundnes, but their loynes are filled with illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and their reines do afflict them euen vnto night)</hi> was free from turpitude! <hi>S. Gregory</hi> eſteemed it a rare degree of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, <note place="margin">6. <hi>Moral. c.</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>When Gods grace</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>perfectly rewardeth ſome ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinent, not to feele the stings, or violence of the motions of the flesh.</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:183906:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> But this woman felt neither the violence of the motions, nor the motion it ſelfe. O what iewell of chaſtity did the earth looſe! how much did heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gaine by her death! But now let vs conſider her patience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>Of her ſingular Patience.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>OVr Sauiour affirmeth Patience to be ſo neceſſary to euery man, that he declareth, that therin we ſhall poſſeſſe our ſoules; as if without it, man were not maiſter <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> of him ſelfe, but were carryed hither and thither with the blind fury of affection: and this vertue in the La. Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len was not inferiour to the former. For it appeared ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable <note place="margin">Her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall patience.</note> to all that knew her, not for a certaine time, nor in ſome company, nor vpon certaine occaſions, but in all the whole courſe of her life. Nor did ſhe carry her ſelfe patiently towards ſtrangers only, or her equals, but euen towards her familiars, and her very ſeruants; from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending of whome, if they had offended her, ſhe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed <note place="margin">She wold nor chide her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants leaſt ſhe ſhould be angry.</note> to abſtaine, leaſt (as ſhe often ſayd) ſhe ſhould be moued to anger; being more carefull of her patience and tranquillity of mind, then of conſcruing her temporall eſtate. For when any matter was committed deſeruing reprehenſion, ſhe accuſtomed to ſay to one: <hi>Goe, and chide ſuch a one.</hi> And ſo farre was ſhe from the vice of chiding, that ſhe vnderſtood not all the words which brauling <note place="margin">A mild ſpeach of the Lady.</note> people accuſtome to vſe; and therfore when not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her death, ſhe heard one woman ſcolding with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, ſhe openly ſayd, that till that day ſhe neuer heard ſuch kind of ſpeaches. She vſed to ſay: A good word is as eaſily ſpoken, as an euill. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of her <note place="margin">Her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:183906:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> not only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> which <note place="margin">Patience ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries.</note> her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> him. It was doubtles an act of great patience, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les an iniury of her ſeruant, but a greater to conceale it; but the greateſt, in that ſhe accuſtomed to induce her aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by benefits to acknowledge their fault. And ſo much did this her Patience preuaile with two of her notorious aduerſaries, that vpon their knees they asked her pardon <note place="margin">People of all ages and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions delighted in her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation.</note> of their offence. And this her patience was in her ſo much the more admirable, as ſhe was by nature cholerike, and ſo much choler was found in her body after her death, that ſuch as ſaw it, and knew her moſt meeke manner of liuing, were exceedingly amazed therat. So milde and ſweet was her conuerſation, that ſhe allured people of all conditions to her company; and, which was to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, euery age, euery degree, and both ſexes did ſeeme e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually to be ſurpriſed with the loue of her company; and ſhe did ſo accommodate her ſelfe to the ciuill comport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of euery one, that yet ſhe admitted nothing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of her ſelfe, or vnbeſeeming her age and grauity. She was very vnwilling to offend any by word, geſture, or act; yea to take from others occaſion of complayning, whatſoeuer ſeemed moleſtfull, ſhe tooke it her ſelfe: and that which <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> calleth a great gift of God in his <note place="margin">She con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealeth the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of others.</note> Mother, that when one had ſecretly complayned vnto her of another: <hi>She would ſpeake nothing of the one vnto the other, but what might tend to their reconciliation;</hi> this, in this woman was rare and perſpicuous. And this kind of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience ſhe exerciſed, not only when ſhe had her perfect health, but euen in her grieuous ſicknes, as ſhall appeare <note place="margin">9. <hi>Conf. c.</hi> 9.</note> hereafter in our relation of her extreme infirmity, wherin not content with the torments which her diſeaſe did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, ſhe ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inuocated almighty God with theſe words: <note place="margin">Excellent patience.</note> O Lord, more paine, and more patience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:183906:17"/>
               <head>Of her prompt Obedience.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>HOw obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the pious Lady was, may eaſily be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by what we haue related of her ſingular hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility. For what would ſhe diſdaine to do, who had ſo humble a conceit of her ſelfe? what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement would ſhe refuſe to performe, who vncommaunded executed the moſt baſt kind of ſeruice? And how ſeriouſly may we thinke ſhe obeyed her husband, who ſo diligently atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her Lady? Out of doubt, ſhe both piouſly obeyed her parents, for which almighty God bleſſed her with long life, and carefully ſubmited her ſelfe to her husband, &amp; ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitouſly fulfilled his will, wherupon ſhe often ſayd, that <note place="margin">The ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the La. of her obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> ſhe left her will at S. <hi>Iames,</hi> which was the place of her Mariage. Beſides ſhe religiouſly ſubmitted her ſelfe to her Confeſſor, wherof I could alleadge many examples, but I will be content with one. This humble and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Lady, by counſaile of her Phiſician, and by admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her Confeſſor in her laſt infirmity, and euen on Aſh-wedneſday (which ſhe neuer did in her life before, and did piouſly abhorre it) was perſwaded to eate fleſh. She then preferred the requeſt of her Confeſſor, before <note place="margin">She fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall.</note> her owne will, and her moſt ancient and Religious cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome. Yet ſhe did this with ſuch caution &amp; feare of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall, that ſhe commaunded her litle Grandchildren to be out of the way, leaſt being vncapable of vnderſtanding the cauſe wherfore ſhe did eat fleſh, they might afterward abuſe her example. For which cauſe alſo, when a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant comming into her chamber, found her eating of fleſh in the lent, ſhe forgot not to aduertiſe him, that ſhe did not eat fleſh for gluttony, or in contempt of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the Church, but rather in obedience to the Church, which, by counſaile both of the ſpirituall and temporall Phiſitians, giueth leaue to the infirme to eat fleſh. Another
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:183906:17"/> tyme alſo, when to comfort and encourage her, it was told her, that ſhe being ſo extreme weake, and eating fleſh by the counſaile of both her Phiſitians, might me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit more by eating, then others by faſting, ſhe requeſted to forbeare ſuch kind of ſpeach, leaſt people ouer prone to giue way to gluttony, ſhould contemne faſting. But when it was anſwered her, that not ſimple eating, but only eating of obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was preferred before faſting, for ſo much as in faſting, is abſtinence from meate, but in eating of obedience, is abnegation of ones owne will, which people preferre before eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the moſt delicate meat; and that her example was not of ſimple eating, but of eating vpon obedience agaynſt her owne will, wherin ſhe was not lyke to haue too many imitatours; when (I ſay) ſhe heard theſe words, ſhe was ſilent, and ſhewed <note place="margin">A moſt obedient ſaying.</note> her ſelfe ready to be diſpoſed of any way, often vſing theſe words: <hi>Doe with me what you pleaſe, for I will no longer haue my will.</hi> And certaynly ſuch was her obedience all the tyme of her tedious infirmity, eyther in abſtayning <note place="margin">Notable obedience in her ſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes.</note> from that which ſhe deſired, or in accepting what was offered her, that it moued great admiration in all the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded her, who fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d no more difficulty in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning her, then if they had attended an innocent child.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>Of her Liberality towards others.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>OMitting to ſpeake of her liberality towards her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and kinred, or of her hoſpitality towards No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſons, becauſe this is accuſtomed to be attributed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to nature then to vertue, I will only ſpeake of her li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality towards others. She maintayned a great family, which conſiſted of eighty perſons, and ſometimes more, and almoſt all Catholikes. And theſe ſhe maintayned not only for her honour (as is the manner of noble perſons) <note place="margin">Her great family.</note> but alſo to ſupport them in the Catholike Religion; and to theſe ſhe allowed not only plentifull food, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:183906:18"/> wages, but (which is much more to be eſteemed) afforded them the ſame benefit of the word of God, and the Sacraments, that her ſelfe enioyed; and as farre as ſhe could ſecured them from vexations, &amp; perſecution of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes. <note place="margin">How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed of maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike family.</note> Which kind of liberality is farre to be preferred before euen the diſtribution of very great ſummes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in almes. For in this kind of almes, only mony is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, but in the pious liberality of this Lady, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mony is beſtowed but meat, lodging, defence from perſecution, the exerciſe of Religion, and the vſe of the Sacraments and a viſible Church or Company of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes is aſſembled, and conſerued. She maintayned three Prieſts in her houſe, and gaue entertaynment to all that repayred to her, &amp; very ſeldome diſmiſſed any with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the guift of an Angell; ſhe redeemed two out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at her owne coſt, and attempted the lyke for others, and gaue mony to other Catholikes both in common &amp; particuler. Her almes diſtributed euery ſecond day at her gates vnto the poore, were plentifull, and ſuch, as ſome of the richer Proteſtants did calumniate that they augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">Her almes</note> the number of beggers, and nouriſhed their idlenes. When ſhe deſiſted from her prayers, ſhe accuſtomed to ſpend much tyme in ſowing ſhirts or ſmockes for poore men and women, in which exerciſe ſhe ſeemed to take much pleaſure; ſometimes alſo when ſhe had leaſure ſhe viſited the poore in their owne houſes, and ſent them, eyther medecines, or meat, or wood, or mony as ſhe perceyued their need; and when ſhe could not performe this her ſelfe, ſhe ſent her wayting women. Which kind of Charity ſhe omitted not euen in her greateſt, and laſt infirmity, but euen then enquired how it fared with the poore, and lamented their infirmities, when her ſelfe of all other needed moſt commiſeration.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:183906:18"/>
               <head>Of her Zeale and Constancy in ſupporting, and profeſsing the Catholyke Fayth.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>HOw gratefull is is vnto God to profeſſe his fayth, it appeareth by thoſe words of Chriſt our Sauiour: <hi>Euery one that shall confeſſe me before men, I alſo will confeſſe him before my Father.</hi> And alſo on the contrary, how odious it <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.</note> is vnto God to deny his fayth, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uident by that which followeth: <hi>But he that shall deny me before men, I alſo will deny him before my Father which is in heauen.</hi> But how co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant the La. <hi>Magdalen</hi> was, not only in keeping, but euen in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the fayth of Chriſt, is euident, not by one act, but by the whole progreſſe of her life. For in thoſe times, ſo turbulent, &amp; ſo exceeding ſubiect to mutation vnder the Kings <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. and <hi>Edward</hi> the ſix, and Q <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> ſhe remayned moſt conſtant in her fayth. And if in the beginning of the raigne of Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſhe went ſometimes to hereticall Churches, that may rather be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the defect of inſtruction, then want of zeale. For when ſhe vnderſtood it to be vnlawfull, ſhe did moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly abhorre it. And albeit that vnder Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured no other perſecution for matter of Religion, then that ſhe was once accuſed to the pretended Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> her houſe twice ſcarched, and her Prieſt once taken, and impriſonned; yet was ſhe prepared to ſuffer whatſoeuer it ſhould pleaſe God, and did expoſe herſelfe to the perill therof. For wheras ſhe had two goodly Manſion houſes, the one vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Thames ſide neere Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don-bridge, in which, from the firſt beginning of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">The houſe of the La. Magd. a common refuge for Prieſts.</note> by Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was a common retire for Prieſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in, and going out of England; and alſo a refuge for ſuch as reſided in London; wherin alſo one Prieſt had his reſidence, to miniſter the Sacraments to ſuch Catholikes as reſorted thither. In this houſe happened a matter wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:183906:19"/> obſeruation, which by the way I thought requiſite to relate. When in the chappell of this houſe (which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time appertayned to the Canons-Regular) ſome perſons did dig in the place where the high Altar had formerly ſtood, vnder the ſame altar, or neere therunto they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a leaden coffin, &amp; within it the body of a Religious man lapped in linnen, and bound hard with cords, there bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed many yeares before, ſo ſound, flexible, and of ſo liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a colour, as it ſeemed aliue. The La. Magdalen, as her ſelfe told me, putting her fingers into his mouth, did a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle pull out his tongue, which was fleſhly red and dry; &amp; another with a knife cut a ſlaſh in the fleſh, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſeemed very ſound and fatty, no ſigne appearing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Balme, or any other thing that could conſerue that body from corruption. And of this matter many eye witneſſes worthy of credit are yet liuing. In her other houſe, which, being diſtant foure miles from <hi>Hastings,</hi> of that famous field which there was fought betweene <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> the Conquerour and King <hi>Herald,</hi> is called <hi>Battell,</hi> where herſelfe with her family did for the moſt part re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, ſhe kepr three Prieſts, one of whome was <hi>M. Thomas More,</hi> great grandchild, and direct heire of that famous <hi>Syr Thomas More</hi> ſometime Lord Chauncellor of England, &amp; a moſt worthy Martyr; who ſeeking to participate rather of the vertues, then of the lands of his great grandfather, hauing reſigned vnto his yonger brother a moſt ample patrimony, &amp; being worthily adorned with learning &amp; vertues, and made Prieſt, deuoted himſelfe wholy to the conuerſion of his Country; in which induſtry he hath laudably employed himſelfe theſe 20. yeares. Another was <hi>M. Thomas Smith</hi> Bachelor of diuinity, a man no leſſe venerable for his learning, worthy piety, and vnwearyed endeuour in helping his Country, then for his grauity of yeares. The third was my ſelfe. Theſe did miniſter the word of God and the Sacraments, not only to the La. <hi>Magdalen,</hi> and her family, but to all Catholikes repayri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thither. She built a chappell in her houſe (which in ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:183906:19"/> perſecution was to be admired) and there placed a very faire Altar of ſtone, wherto ſhe made an aſcent with ſteps <note place="margin">She built a chappell with a Quier in her houſe.</note> and encloſed it with railes: and to haue euery thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable, ſhe built a Quire for ſingers, and ſet vp a pulpit for the Prieſts, which perhaps is not to be ſeene in all En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland beſides. Heere almoſt euery weeke was a ſermon made, and on ſolemne feaſts the ſacrifice of the Maſſe was celebrated with ſinging, and muſicall inſtruments, and ſometimes alſo with Deacon &amp; ſubdeacon. And ſuch was the concourſe and refort of Catholikes, that ſometimes <note place="margin">Solemne Maſſe ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated.</note> there were 120 together, and 60. communicants at a time had the benefit of the B. Sacrament. And ſuch was the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Catholikes reſident in her houſe, and the multitude <note place="margin">The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort of Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.</note> and note of ſuch as repayred thither, that euen the hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, to the eternall glory of the name of the La. <hi>Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> gaue it the title of <hi>Litle Rome.</hi> O happy woman, and true mayntainer of the Romaine fayth, who, where the very name of <hi>Rome</hi> is to moſt ſo odious, that they vſe all <note place="margin">The houſe of the La. Mag. cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led litle Rome.</note> their induſtry and vtmoſt endeuour to extinguiſh it; there, ſhe did not only preſerue the memory ther of, but made it ſo famous, as ſhe deſerued to haue the title therof giuen to her houſe. Let others nominate their houſes by what ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles they pleaſe, this only title of <hi>Litle Rome,</hi> giuen by Heretikes vnto thy houſe, O Honorable <hi>Magdalen,</hi> by reaſon of the Romane fayth there profeſſed, appeareth more famous, and more illuſtrious then all other titles! Whiles ſhe was preſent either at Maſſe or Sermon, ſhe did not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceale herſelfe for feare to be betrayed by ſome falſe brother, as it ſometimes happeneth in England, but ſhe did ſerue God publikely in the ſight of all, that by her example ſhe might encourage all; and when ſhe walked abroad, by her Beads, or Croſſe which ſhe vſed to weare about her neck, ſhe profeſſed herſelfe to be a Catholike, euen to whatſoeuer Hereticall beholders; and ſo manifeſt was her religion, that ſcarce any in England had heard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r name, who knew her not alſo to be a Catholike. She <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>dered none from hearing Maſſe in her houſe, if any
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:183906:20"/> Catholike had but the leaſt knowledge of them, vſing theſe words: <hi>Let theſe poore people come, they deſire comfort as much as we.</hi> And that which to others did ſtrike a feare of trobles, was vnto her occaſion of great ioy: to wit, when on feſtiuall dayes, ſhe ſaw a great number of Catholiks in her Chappell, in ſo much as ſhe would ſometimes ſhed <note place="margin">She offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth leaue to print Catholike books in her houſe.</note> teares for ioy, and would thanke God, that by her mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſo many pious ſoules receiued ſpirituall conſolation. Yea ſo far ſtreched the fortitude of this bleſſed woman, in propagating the Catholike fayth, that ſhe twice offered me leaue to ſet vp a Preſſe to print Catholike bookes in her houſe; which had bin done but that it was moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, and almoſt impoſſible in ſuch an ample family to to conceale ſuch a matter from Heretikes. This her coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Conſtancy bred her great Enuie, in her Hereticall neighbours: wherwith ſome of them being moued, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented her name, and the names of almoſt all her family ſo the Iudges in publike aſſiſes, for not obſeruing the law of comming to Church euery month. By which law it is commanded, that whatſoeuer perſon of the age of 16. yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſhall abſtaine, for a month, from the Proteſtant Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſhalbe confined within the compaſſe of fiue miles of his houſe, and ſhall pay, at the choyce of the King, either 20.<hi rend="sup">••</hi> euery month, or two thirds of his lands &amp; teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, with the loſſe of all his goods: &amp; if he keep any Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <note place="margin">The La. Mag. firſt of all the Nobility in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d accuſed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſtatute of going to hereticall Churches</note> ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, he ſhall pay beſides for each one, 10.<hi rend="sup">••</hi> euery month, Vpon which law the La. Magdalen was the firſt of the Nobility, that euer in England was accuſed in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike iudgment. But ſhe was ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being terrified with this moſt hard proceeding, or diſmiſſing of any of her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, that, hauing intelligence therof, with a pleaſing Countenance ſhe ſayd: <hi>If the King will haue two thirds of mine eſtate, I will ioyfully liue with the rest, and I thank God, who hath permitted me to enjoy it hitherto, and now permitteth that it be taken from me, for profeſsion of his fayth.</hi> When there was danger of ſearching her houſe, ſhe was more ſollicitous of her Prieſts then of herſelfe, and when in the time of that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:183906:20"/> notorious powder-treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhe was terrifyed with extreme <note place="margin">Her man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in preſent perill.</note> and imminent dangers, that ſhe ſhould not be able to keep a Prieſt in her houſe, ſhe did not yet giue way ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, but diſmiſſing the aduertiſer, with a manly courage and full of confidence in God, ſhe ſayd to her Confeſſor: <hi>Let vs ſay the litanies, and commit this matter to God.</hi> And as well at other times often, as when ſhe lay in her extreme infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, <note place="margin">She redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth two of her neereſt kinred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church.</note> ſhe ſtrictly commaunded her children, encouraged her ſeruants, and importunatly exhorted all perſons, to neglect the wealth of the world, conſtantly to retaine the Catholike fayth, and to repoſe their hopes in God. At which time Almighty God gaue vnto her this conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that by her example and admonitions ſhe reduced two of her neereſt kinred into the lap of the church. And certainly it is to be much attributed to her Piety, that wheras ſhe left liuing aboue thirty of her children, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phewes <note place="margin">She de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth her children might ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer death for the Catholike fayth.</note> and Neeces, ſhe left them all conſtant profeſſors of the Catholike fayth. And albeit ſhe moſt tenderly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted her children; yet ſhe ſo much preferred fayth before nature, that ſhe would often ſay, ſhe ſhould exceedingly reioyce to ſee any of them to dye for the Catholike fayth. Neither do I doubt, but if Almighty God had tryed her, we ſhould haue ſeene in her the courage of the Mother of the Machabees.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>Of her notable Piety towards God.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XII.</head>
               <p>THe nurſe of all Vertue is piety &amp; deuotion towards God, which in the Lady <hi>Magdalen</hi> was very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable. For ſhe was euery day preſent at the morning and euening ſeruice which by her Prieſts was daily ſayd <note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion of the La. Mag. vnto the Maſſe.</note> in her chappell. For the moſt part, ſhe did euery day heare three Maſſes, &amp; more would willingly haue heard, if ſhe might: and ſuch was her affection to this diuine ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, that when vpon any occaſion in the winter it was
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:183906:21"/> ſayd before day, ſhe in that cold and vnſeaſonable time, could not contayne herſelfe in her bed, but riſing, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not to be abſent from that heauenly Sacrifice. In her priuate deuotions, ſhe did euery day ſay three offices, <note place="margin">Her daily priuate prayers.</note> that is, of the B. Virgin, of the Holy Ghoſt, and of the Holy Croſſe; wherto ſhe added at leaſt three Roſaries, the Ieſus Pſalter, the 50. prayers of <hi>S. Brigit,</hi> which becauſe they beginne with O, are commonly called her 15. Oes, and the common Litanyes; and finally ſometymes the office of the dead. Which prayers, when in her infirmity ſhe could not ſay her ſelfe, ſhe procured to be ſayd by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, diſtributing to euery one a part. And that I may <note place="margin">What time ſhe ſpent in prayer.</note> comprehend much in few words, ſhe ſpent a very great part of the day, and much of the night in prayer. For ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing early in the morning, ſhe for the moſt part emploied the reſt of the tyme, euen till the houre of dinner in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and ſometymes ſhe would retyre her ſelfe alone after dinner into the chappell to pray; as alſo before ſupper ſhe ſpent an houre, or often two houres in prayer; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe went to bed ſhe omitted not the Litanyes, and the examen of her conſcience. And I haue ſome tymes obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that on Chriſtmas Eue at night, from an houre before midnight till a litle before dinner, ſhe neuer went out of the Chappell but only a little to attire herſelfe; but was al that tyme watchfully employed in prayers, and deuout actions. She was often found in her chamber proſtrate on the ground in prayer, albeyt ſhe accuſtomed, when the heat of deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did moue her, to ſhut the dores. In the night alſo, when others tooke their ſleepe, ſhe was heard of her women to ſay her Beads, which to that end did alwayes hang at her beds ſyde. And as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> writeth of <hi>S. Lea, She instructed her family more by example then by word,</hi> &amp; with her piety induced all to deuotion. And although <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 24.</note> ſhe was by priuiledge of her age exempted from faſting, yet did she piouſly obſerue all the faſts of the Lent, the <note place="margin">She did often faſt.</note> Ember dayes, and whatſoeuer other, eyther commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Church, or introduced by the pious cuſtome
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:183906:21"/> of the Country, as are the faſts of Fridayes, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: to all which, of her owne deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe added ſome wedneſdayes. O right pious woman, and imitating that holy widdow, which <hi>did not depart from the Temple, ſeruing</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>God day and night, in faſting and prayer!</hi> And ſhe was ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with loue vnto prayer and deuotion, that the care of worldly eſtate was tedious vnto her, which ſhe would willingly haue impoſed vpon ſome other, &amp; did ſomety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferre with me of that matter, that ſhe might who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deuote her ſelf vnto God, but that there were ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments which her ſelfe could not remoue. She ſhewed a reſpectiue reuerence to her Prieſts, for the honour of <note place="margin">Her exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence to her Prieſts.</note> God, and did moſt humbly on her knees, morning and euening aske their benediction, which ſhe did alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue towards other Prieſts at their comming &amp; going. Which honour exhibited to our Prieſts from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Engliſh Church, as teſtifyeth <hi>S. Bede</hi> in the third booke of his Hiſtory, and 26. Chap. but long tyme intermitted, their frequent deathes for the Catholyke fayth hath reduced; for within 30. yeares, aboue 120. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Prieſts haue bin crowned with Martyrdome in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland. Euery Sunday, and feſtiuall day beſides, ſhe did purge her ſinnes by holy Confeſſion; which ſhe perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <note place="margin">She fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently confeſſed &amp; with great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition.</note> with great preparation of mynd, and diſcuſſion of her conſcience. She opened her ſinnes with exceeding ſincerity, and bewayled them with ſuch abundance of teares, that whoſoeuer had ſeene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, would haue thoght her another ſinfull <hi>Magdalen,</hi> but the hearer of her ſinnes thought of the innocency of <hi>S. Iohn</hi> going into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, <hi>leaſt he should maculate his life with the leaſt idle word.</hi> For what ſhe confeſſed were ſometimes ſo ſmall, that I thought it neceſſary, to aduiſe her to accuſe herſelfe of ſome former ſinnes, fearing leaſt otherwiſe there might want matter of abſolution. And yet as I ſayd, ſhe did ſo bitterly lament them, that ſhe forced me to teares; for which cauſe I deſired to heare her confeſſion before I confeſſed my owne ſinnes. For in her, as S. <hi>Hierome</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:183906:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:183906:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:183906:23"/> of S. <hi>Paula, Thou wouldest beleiue to be fountaines of teares, the ſo bewailed ſleight ſinnes, as thou wouldest think her to be guilty</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">In vita Paulae.</note> 
                  <hi>of grieuous crimes.</hi> Euery yeare, at leaſt once, whiles I had care of her, ſhe made a generall confeſſion of all her ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any ſcruple, but that ſhe might obtaine that, which the Prophet, hauing alredy obtained pardon of his ſinne, requeſted when he ſayd: <hi>Wash me more from my ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.</note> 
                  <hi>and clenfe me from my ſinne;</hi> and with all, that ſhe might the more humble her ſelfe, and haue her ſinnes alwayes before her eyes. And albeit ſhe was very ſollicitous in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſing her conſcience; yet ſhe did frequently requeſt me, that if I perceiued any vice in her conuerſation, I ſhould not omit to admoniſh her therof. And ſhe was ſo ſeuere towards her ſelfe, that ſhe would deſire more pennance then was enioyned her, and would ſay, that ſhe neuer <note place="margin">She deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red more pennance then was enioyned her.</note> met with a Confeſſor that would enioyne her ſufficient ſatisfaction. And for that reaſon perhaps, for ſome Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes before her laſt ſicknes, ſhe accuſtomed euery weeke after her confeſſion to giue me ten ſhillings, to diſtribute in almes, ſo to ſupply that which to her ſeemed wanting in the impoſition of her pennance. Concerning which Mony, this happened worthy of obſeruation, that when ſhe was ſick, &amp; could not according to that cuſtome giue <note place="margin">An ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the mony ſhe gaue for ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</note> me euery weeke that certaine ſumme, ſhe commaunded one of her ſeruants, to deliuer me ſuch mony as he had of hers, which mony came not to a farthing more, nor leſſe then ten ſhillings, for euery week ſhe liued. This then was the piety of this worthy woman in confeſſing frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in confeſſing with great ſincerity, contrition, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of ſatisfying God for her ſins; wherto was anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able her like deuotion towards the moſt B. Sacrament of <note place="margin">Her piety towards the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt.</note> the Euchariſt. For when in this manner ſhe had purged her ſoule from ſinne, ſhe came with an hungry deſire to receiue the bread of life, and with what externall reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and humiliation of body, ſhe both came to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Altar of Chriſt, and returned thence, with what tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res in her eyes, and with what reuerence in her counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:183906:23"/> ſhe receiued that ſacred banquet; they well percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued who beheld her. But with what in teriour piety, and with what enflamed charity towards God, ſhe entertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her Sauiour in her heart, he only ſaw, who ſeeth the ſecrets of harts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the admirable Prouidence of God, towards the La. Magdalen.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <p>AS this holy woman had a peculiar care to ſerue &amp; pleaſe God, ſo it appeareth that correſpondently he had a particuler prouidence, and care ouer her, wherof I will alleadge a few examples. Whiles ſhe was a marryed woman ſhe fell into an extreme, and continuall griefe &amp; affliction of mind, vpon the ruine of her family procured (as ſhe ſometimes ſayd) by him in whome ſhe had placed the hope of beſt reliefe therof; which melancholy affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction being ſuch as exceeded the art of all Phiſitians, and the counſaile and comfort of her friends, almighty God at length compaſſionating his ſeruant, vouchſafed to cure her by another meanes. For in a dreame (as ſhe particuler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">God cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth her tedious affliction.</note> related vnto me) it was clearly and manifeſtly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated vnto her, what ſhe ſhould do to be freed of her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward griefe. Which when ſhe had performed, (it being a very pious action) ſhe was inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly cured of that affliction of mind, which no humane art, medicine, or counſaile could preuaile in. Of this triall, as ſhe often confeſſed, ſhe obtayned a better knowledge of her ſelfe, and more bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any other thing; in ſo much that ſhe confidently affirmed, that by her owne experience, ſhe had learned that God worketh all things for our good. And by this meanes almighty God did meruailouſly free her from ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall deſolations, &amp; did conuert them to her aduantage and conſolation; neither did he leſſe protect her from her corporall enemies. For wheras ſome few years before her
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:183906:24"/> death certaine Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, in hatred of her Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſought the deſtruction of her, and all her family, yet did they not preuaile in their malice. For the principall of them <hi>Syr</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement of God vpon the heretikes that ſoght the ruine of the La. Mag.</note> 
                  <hi>Tho. May,</hi> being a Knight and Iuſtice of peace, and hauing giuen commaundment for apprehending the ſeruants of the La. <hi>Magdalen,</hi> was himſelfe a litle after ignominiouſly conuented before publike authority, and caſt into priſon for debt, where he lay long, and at the ſetting forth of this worke, was ſhamefully diſmiſſed of the Commiſſion of the Peace. But the author &amp; firebrand of all euils was <hi>Nicholas Cobbe,</hi> who a litle after he began to ſeeke the ruine of the La. <hi>Magdalen,</hi> had a knife thruſt into his belly by his owne wife; &amp; being for ſome hainous fact apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by officers, and euen by heretikes purſued to puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did at length by letters beg pardon of the La. <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen;</hi> and what affliction yet expecteth him, almighty God knoweth. The third inueterate Heretike called <hi>N. Benet,</hi> who perceyuing that nothing, of what himſelfe and his Confederates had conſpired agaynſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout Lady, tooke effect, on a market-day held at <hi>Battell,</hi> falling on this knees before the gate-houſe of the Viſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe, did vomit out his bitter imprecation, praying God to confound her, and all her family. But the dart which the impious fellow caſt againſt heauen, did ſoone fall v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his owne head. For the third day after going early in the morning out of his houſe, he drowned himſelfe in a pit at the townes end, towards <hi>London:</hi> Whereupon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken vp by Proteſtants, &amp; by their iudgement fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d guilty of his owne death, he was buryed like a dog in the high way. At another time alſo when (as before is ſayd) <note place="margin">Note the ſpeedy iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God.</note> ſhe was called in queſtion for not going to hereticall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, ſhe was ſo farre from incurring any detriment ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as that it wrought her more ſecurity then before. For the Kings Councell by their publike letters addreſſed to the Attorny Generall dated the 19. of Aprill 1607. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded that no ſentence ſhould proceed agaynſt her. Which letters becauſe they teſtify both the true allegiance
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:183906:24"/> of the Lady <hi>Magdalen</hi> to the King in temporalityes, and alſo that her moleſtation was meerly for Religion, I will here ſetdowne part of them, out of the originall which is <note place="margin">The La. Mag. que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is otherwiſe faythfull to her Prince.</note> in my cuſtody. <hi>For ſo much</hi> (ſay they) <hi>as the Lady Montague the wife of Antony Viſcount Montague deceaſed, is lately called in question for default of conformity in Religion according to the lawes of this Kingdome; in regard that she is a Noble-woman, aged, and by reaſon of her fidelity, in the tyme of Q. Elizabeth, was neuer cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in queſtion, it pleaſeth the Kings Maiesty that in her old yeares she be free from moleſtation. Theſe therfore, shalbe to require you, that you forthwith doe procure the accuſation which is preſented a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her in the County of Suſſex or elſe where, to be remoued by writ of Certiorari, into his Maiesties Court of the Kings bench, &amp; therby you shall haue power to stay all proceſſe againſt her perſon, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon that preſentment, or whatſoeuer other, till we shallbe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther certifyed.</hi> And in the ſame manner, when vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ſearch for the powder-traytors, Proteſtants did often ſearch her houſe, ſhe obtayned letters from the Kings Councell dated the 5. of Aprill 1606. And ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by ten of the ſame Councell, that none beſides fower by her ſelf nominated, ſhould ſearch her houſe. By which <note place="margin">The La. Mag. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing herſelfe to perill for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came more free from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> letters ſhe obtayned, that herſelfe, whoſe houſe eſpecially was alwayes free to all Catholikes, &amp; who, in admitting Catholikes to the Sacraments, expoſed herſelfe to dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger more then all others, proued thence forward to be more free from perill then any elſe. Whiles ſhe lay in Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don in the yeare 1606. a Proteſtant ſeeing one goe into her houſe, whome he ſuſpected (but falſely) to be one of thoſe whome the King had proclaymed guilty of the powder-treaſon, declared the ſame to the Kings Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, who inſtantly authorized Officers that moſt watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully beſet both hers, and the adioyning houſes, from Wedneſday at two of the clocke in the morning, till Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday noone following, and in that tyme very diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſearched hers, but eſpecially her neighbours houſes. The Lady <hi>Magdalens</hi> Prieſt was then abſent, who was gone towards <hi>Battell,</hi> ſhe intending immediately to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:183906:25"/> him; but vnderſtanding that two of her family were fallen grieuouſly ſick, inſtantly taking horſe, returned to <hi>London,</hi> the ſame day that the ſearch began. But almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">Her Prieſt twice eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped the handes of heretikes.</note> God ſo protected the Lady <hi>Magdalen,</hi> that at the very inſtant when the Prieſt, ſuſpecting no danger, entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe, the Watchmen for a quarter of an hower were gone aſide. And euen two dayes after when it was eſteemed moſt dangerous for him to remayne there any longer, he went againe out of the houſe in the middeſt of the watch, not one of them apprehending him, albeit amongſt them there were three that knew him well, to be a Prieſt, and did ſpeake of him to each other, and with their fingers pointed at him. Not many monthes after the ſame Prieſt going from the houſe of the Viſcounteſſe at <hi>Battell,</hi> was diſcouered to the aforeſayd impious <hi>Cobbe,</hi> &amp; <note place="margin">Againe an other time</note> the Prieſt being ſcarce out of ſight, <hi>Cobbe</hi> hauing a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment malicious deſire to apprehend him, ran euery way to hyre a horſe to purſue him; but Almighty God did ſo preſerue the Lady <hi>Magdalen,</hi> that he permitted not any Proteſtant, though her grieuous enemyes, to lend <hi>Cobbe</hi> a horſe, nor ſuffered him to follow the Prieſt a foote, or by out-cry (as is the manner in England) to rayſe the people to purſue him; wheras the Prieſt, not ſuſpecting any danger, walked on a foote pace, expecting one that was to accompany him, might eaſily haue byn apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Both which eſcapes the Prieſt himſelfe aſcribed to the piety of this Lady whome God protected, leaſt her Prieſt being taken, her lyfe had byn brought in queſtion for entertayning him. With the rehearſall of one admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing which happened in her houſe, I will end the diſcourſe of theſe things. There ſtood vpright agaynſt a <note place="margin">An admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thing of an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar-ſtone.</note> wall a great marble ſtone, which in Catholike tymes had byn an Altar-ſtone for the ſeruice of almighty God; and a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of curioſity deſirous to ſee that ſide therof which reſted agaynſt the wall, ſo drew the ſtone towards her, as it fell vpon her. And albeit the ſtone was of that huge greatnes and weight, as eight men could hardly with
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:183906:25"/> whatſoeuer leauers remoue it from one place to another, and nothing lay betweene it and the woman that might ſaue her from the fall of it, yet was it ſo taken vp without the leaſt hurt of the woman, as if a bed of fethers, not ſo huge a ſtone, had fallen vpon her. Whereupon the ſtone was by commandement of the Lady <hi>Magdalen,</hi> remoued into the Chappell, conſecrated agayne to diuine ſeruice, and applyed to his former vſe. But now, though with griefe, let vs come to declare her death. <hi>For who</hi> (as S. <hi>Hierome</hi> writeth of <hi>S. Paula) can with vnwatered eyes relate the death of the Lady</hi> Magdalen?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>Of her happy Paſsage vnto God.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XIIII.</head>
               <p>VVHen ſhe had piouſly and bleſſedly liued com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete 70. yeares, &amp; had ſeene her third genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and aboue thirty perſons of her iſſue, and all by the grace of God Profeſſors of the Catholike fayth, the next day after her birth-day, to wit, the 21. of Ianuary of the yeare 1608. at which tyme there was ſuch an extreme froſt <note place="margin">An extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me froſt in England.</note> in England, that the Riuer <hi>Thames</hi> being frozen, men, horſes, and carts paſſed ouer vpon the ice, yea meat being roſted theron, people did banquet there, as vpon the firme land; at ſuch tyme (I ſay) as the froſt gaue ſuch a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <note place="margin">The Lady Magd. falleth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy.</note> horrour, the Lady <hi>Magdalen</hi> fell into a Palſy, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhe loſt the motion of the right ſide of her body, and much wanted the vſe of her tongue. Within two dayes, the moſt prudent Lady perceiued her diſeaſe to be mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, neither yet did ſhe deſire any medicine, or ſent for <note place="margin">How ſhe prepared for death.</note> any Phiſician, but calling for her Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſor, deſired to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of all the ſacraments of Chriſt, which in ſuch caſe are requiſite. Which hauing with exceeding deuotion &amp; tranquillity of mind receiued, &amp; deliuering her laſt will and teſtament to one, ſhe prepared herſelfe for death, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſting that thence forward ſhe might be free from all moleſtation of temporall affaires. But almighty God, for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:183906:26"/> the greater glory of his name, for her merit, and our edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, did prolong her infirmity for eleuen whole wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, to wit, till the eight of Aprill. In which time it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <note place="margin">Her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable meeknes and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</note> be vttered, what admirable patience ſhe ſhewed, both in words and deeds, neuer wayward, or tedious, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes thankefull, euen to the meaneſt of her ſeruants, when they had done any thing about her; and oftentimes euen in her extremeſt torments, praying God to increaſe both her paine and patience. Her accuſtomed prayers (as before I ſayd) ſhe diſtributed amongſt her friends. She heard Maſſe euery day, at which time ſhe would be lifted vp in her bed, which ſhe omitted not, euen the laſt day of her life. There did hang at her beds feete a ſiluer Croſſe <note place="margin">Her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion in her ſicknes.</note> guilded, of Chriſt crucified, which was ſometimes her Grandmothers, the famous Counteſſe of <hi>Shrewsbury;</hi> to it ſhe did very frequently lift her eyes, and ſometimes (as ſhe could) her hands, without vttering a word, but with great ſignes of deuotion: ſometimes ſhe would double thoſe petitions of the <hi>Pater noſter: Fiat voluntas tua ſicut in cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo &amp; in terra. Dimitte nobis debita nostra, ſicut &amp; nos dimit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imus debitoribus nostris. Et ne nos inducas in tentationem.</hi> At other ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſhe prayed with vs, or gaue eare to the reading of the Paſſion of Chriſt, or ſome pious booke, and now &amp; then would admoniſh vs to put her in mind of heauen, &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things. Sometimes ſhe enquired the eſtate of other ſick perſons; &amp; as occaſion was preſented, ſhe did exhort Catholikes to conſtancy in their fayth; and ſometimes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſhe ſpake to Heretikes of imbracing the Catholike fayth. But how much at that time ſhe was enflamed with the loue of God, euen by this it may appeare, that once ſhe exceedingly loathing a certaine potion, when after many importunate requeſts one had deſired her to take the ſame for his loue, who for her dranke vinegar &amp; gall, preſently without giuing any anſwere, ſhe tooke the cup and dranke it all vp; ſo ſodenly did the memory of the Paſſion of Chriſt make that ſeeme ſweet, which before was very loathſome vnto her. She ſo little feared death,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:183906:26"/> that from the beginning of her ſicknes, to vs who much deſired her life, ſhe ſeemed too much to deſire her death; &amp; therfore when we did propoſe vnto her the examples of <note place="margin">She rather wiſheth then fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth death</note> S. <hi>Paul,</hi> S. <hi>Martin,</hi> and others, who for the conſolation of their friends were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to liue, ſhe would humbly anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were: <hi>The will of God be done.</hi> And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> once, ſhe falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſound, her ſeruant cryed out in lamentation; as ſoone as ſhe returned to her ſelfe, ſhe reprehended her, ſaying: <hi>Weep not for me, but weep for thy ſinnes, and I command thee that thou pray not for my life.</hi> O ſingular confidence of a pure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience! O contempt of this life, and deſire of the future! After this patient and pious manner did the La. <hi>Magdalen</hi> ſpend that tedious time of her grieuous infirmity, wherin certayne things were obſerued, which perhaps may ſeeme ſpeciall markes of her excellent piety towards God, and <note place="margin">The body of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Magd. breathed a ſweet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour.</note> of his diuine fauour towards her. For albeyt there was nothing about her, that could produce any ſweet odour, yea euery day oyntment applyed to her necke and arme for cure of the Palſy, which gaue a loathſome ſmell, yet one day her body ſeemed to yield a pleaſing ſauour, which not only Catholikes, but euen ſome Proteſtants which then by accident were preſent, did feele, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring, demaunded whence that ſweet odour was. To others it ſeemed another kind of ſauour, yet moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious and beyond all common ſauours. To me it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med much like ſweet balme, ſo that reflecting on the odour of vertue which ſhe left behind her both to Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes and Proteſtants, I reputed that ſaying of <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> to be fulfilled in her: <hi>Sicut balſamum aromatizans odorem dedi.</hi> Another tyme alſo of her ſicknes, a certayne very <note place="margin">A moſt de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licious ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour came forth of the place where he accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to pray.</note> graue &amp; pious man kneeling to pray without the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, but behind the place wherin ſhe accuſtomed to pray did fiue or ſix tymes feele a certaine breathing of the moſt delicious ſauour that euer he felt in his lyfe, to come forth of the Chappell; which ſauour he likened to the gumme of the balme-tree, yet far exceeding all earthly odour, and filled him with exceeding admiration and pleaſure.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:183906:27"/> But what doe we admire ſo ſweet a ſauour to proceed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the place where the Lady <hi>Magdalen</hi> accuſtomed to pray, when ſhe (as the Apoſtle ſayth) <hi>Was a ſweet odour of Chriſt in euery place?</hi> Another thing which to me ſeemeth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of conſideration, was, that wheras the Phiſitian three or foure dayes before her death, gaue vs hope, either of recouering her health, or at leaſt of prolonging her life, neither indeed did there appeare to vs any ſigne of immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent death; neuertheleſſe the ſeauenth of Aprill, which was the day before her death, ſhe requeſted me to intreat my brethen the other Prieſts (for we were then fiue) that we would all that day ſay maſſe for her in honour of the Bleſſed Virgin: and I demaunding of her, to what end <note place="margin">The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable perfection of the La. Magd.</note> ſhe deſired thoſe maſſes to be celebrated; <hi>That</hi> (ſayd ſhe) I <hi>may haue no will but the will of God, and that his most ſacred will may be fulfilled in me, either in life, or death.</hi> O admirable perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this woman, prepared either to liue or dye, as it ſhould pleaſe God, and of herſelfe deſirous of neither, but only of the fulfilling of his diuine pleaſure! And behold, wheras before this time (as is ſayd) we ſaw no ſignes of imminent death, not long after the celebration of the Maſſes, the very pangs of death did aſſault her, neyther did they euer leaue her, till they bereaued her of this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall life. And albeit thoſe pangs were very violent and continuall from Thurſday three of the clocke in the after <note place="margin">Death ſpeedily enſued af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhe ſaid ſhe was prepared for lyfe or death.</note> noone, till almoſt midnight of the day following, which was the eight of Aprill, when ſhe gaue vp her Ghoſt; yet did ſhe perſeuere with the ſame admirable patience and tranquillity of mind. In ſo much that the Friday mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, being asked how ſhe had paſſed the precede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t night, ſhe anſwered: <hi>The best of all that euer I paſsed.</hi> For the moſt prudent woman perceyued death to draw on, and that night to open vnto her a day which was neuer to haue end. Whiles her ſenſes continued, ſhe prayed with vs, &amp; in one hand ſhe held a Croſſe till her forces fayled; in the other a hallowed light, which ſhe held ſo faſt euen af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her death, that without force it could not be wreſted
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:183906:27"/> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her. Her laſt words which could be vnderſtood, were <note place="margin">She pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth.</note> thoſe of our Sauiour: <hi>Into thy hands</hi> (O Lord) <hi>I commend my ſpirit;</hi> which without any reſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or reluctation ſhe pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceably yielded vp, a litle before midnight: at which time, as the Scripture ſayth, <hi>There was a clamour made, Behold the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.</note> 
                  <hi>bridegrome commeth, go ye forth to meet him:</hi> ſhe with the holy women, within the Octaues of our Lords Reſurrection, aroſe out of this valley of teares, &amp; her lampe being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, entred, as we hope, with the Bridegrome to the Mariage. Her bowels were buryed at <hi>Battell</hi> where ſhe dyed, in the monument of her husbands Father, and her body honorably caryed to <hi>Midhurst,</hi> and there layd in the Sepulcher of her husband.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the shape of her Body, and Mind.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XV.</head>
               <p>OF Stature ſhe was very tall, ſo that (as <hi>Saul</hi> amongſt men) ſhe among women of middle ſtature appeared from the ſhoulders vpward, &amp; yet very vpright; neither did ſhe ſtoop in the leaſt manner euen till her death, her very body being erected by her vpright mind. She was fat and groſſe in body; her head was round, &amp; in regard of the greatnes of her body ſeemed litle; her haire in her youth was faire and enclining to yellow, her face beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ttfull and long, her forehead flat, her eyes ſharpe, &amp; of the colour of an haſell-nut; and her ſight ſo continued, as in her laſt dayes, ſhe could diſcerne a tower fifteene miles of, and with ſpectacles could cut euen the fineſt linnen cloth by a threed: and in the ſame manner had ſhe the vſe of all the reſidue of her ſenſes. Her noſe was ſtraight and ſharp, and ſomewhat ſhort, and her chinne great; her cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance very graue and venerable, and her gate vpright, ſober, and full of Maieſty. And this was the externall forme of her body. But concerning her mind, ſhe was of a ſharp wit, and of a notable memory, which yet ſhe ſayd was decayed by her foreſayd long and tedious affliction.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:183906:28"/> She was alſo of a profound iudgment, and of a ſtout and manly courage, ſo that of her may be ſayd, that which is written of <hi>S. Thomas</hi> of Canterbury, viz: <hi>She was humble, but</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                           <desc>••…</desc>
                        </gap>d Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ium tom.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>amongst the humble, for among the potent and proud, she ſeemed more lofty, and potent.</hi> And thus far, to my ability, I haue deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed the life of this pious woman: now let vs heare other mens opinions of her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>Other Mens Iudgements of her.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, the moſt Reuerend Arch-Prieſt of England <hi>M.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Arch-Prieſt and other Prieſts of England.</note> 
                  <hi>George Birckhed</hi> in his letters directed to me, lamented her death, <hi>as it were</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>of a great Mother in Iſrael;</hi> &amp; the Prieſts in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d did euery where extoll her as the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Patroneſſe of the holy fayth, and the ſingular orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Catholike religion in England. A Catholike man of worthy piety, and a man of good iudgement, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit he formerly had knowne her well, yet viſiting her in her ſicknes, and obſeruing her ſingular patience and pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſayd, he would not for any mony haue miſſed the ſight <note place="margin">Alſo of a Catholike Noblema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> of ſuch her excellent vertue. But aboue all, the moſt cleare and euident teſtimony of the vertues of the La. <hi>Magdalen</hi> may be gathered out of the letters of the preſent moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Viſcount <hi>Montague,</hi> whoſe teſtimony is the more eſtimable, in that ſhe was the ſtep-mother of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and himſelfe (as all that know him can witnes) moſt free from flattery, and a moſt conſtant Profeſſour of the Catholike fayth, for which he hath often bin impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <note place="margin">Of the right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague.</note> and at the ſetting forth hereof was priſoner in his owne houſe. This then ſo worthy a man, the yeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the death of the La. <hi>Magdalen,</hi> ſending his daughters to viſit her, in this manner wrote vnto her: <hi>Moſt louing La. and Grandmother, as in my former letters I mentioned, I now in moſt humble and dutifull manner ſend theſe my children vnto your moſt Honourable Ladiship, moſt earnestly deſiring, that euery one</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:183906:28"/> 
                  <hi>of them in their degree may ſo carry themſelues towards your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, that in ſome part they may expreſſe that care which I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes had, to plant in them ſo much loue, and ſuch dutifull reſpect</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The La. Mag. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the life of the Viſcount &amp; of this Father.</note> 
                  <hi>towards your moſt Noble and worthy perſon, as both from them and me, is iustly due vnto her, by whoſe ſingular care, and tender affe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction, I do not only belieue (as I haue partly heard and partly expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced) that my worthy Fathers life, and mine, as by the most prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall earthly inſtrument, were preſerued; but alſo do acknowledge ſo many worthy offices both in matter of temporalities, and in other things of greater moment, in reconciling and conſeruing (whenſoeuer occaſion was offered) the moſt wished fauour of my right Noble</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">She reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileth and conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the fauour of his Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him.</note> 
                  <hi>Grandfather towards me; ſo that ſcarce any La. that was Mother of ſo many children, nor any of leſſe vertue, euer performed the like. Which certainly enforceth me exceedingly to honour and admire your perſon.</hi> In other letters alſo written in the yeare 1606. when he was requeſted by the La. <hi>Magdalen,</hi> to vouchſafe to be Executour of her Will &amp; Teſtament, he anſwered, that although he did neither deſire, nor would willingly ſee the mournfull day of the death of the La. Viſcounteſſe; yet if almighty God ſhould ſo diſpoſe, <hi>Such fidelity</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>as I owe vnto my owne hart, the ſame I promiſe to performe towards your honorable Ladiship.</hi> Which he did afterwards moſt abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly performe in deeds. For he did not only exactly execute her teſtament, but did giue mourning apparell to all his family, wherof the number was great, diſtributed a good ſumme of mony for her ſoule, maintayned the <note place="margin">The Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſed and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</note> whole family of the La. <hi>Magdalen</hi> for three monthes after her death, and diuers her principall ſeruans he entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into his owne ſeruice, and ſome of them he rewarded with ſtipends for their ſeruice done vnto her; &amp; ſuch was the loue betweene him and the Viſcounteſſe, as they may be an example to all ſtep-Mothers, and Sonnes-in-law. <note place="margin">The opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Q. Mary</note> And this was the worthy teſtimony both in words and deeds of this Viſcount, touching the Vertues of the La. <hi>Magdalen.</hi> What eſteeme Queene <hi>Mary</hi> of famous and worthy memory had of her, is formerly alledged. From whoſe iudgement in this matter (though almoſt in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:183906:29"/> goodnes ſhe was far different) her ſiſter Q. <hi>Elizab.</hi> did not diſagree. For thus the La. <hi>Scudamore,</hi> a Lady of her bed-chamber, in her name wrote to the La. <hi>Magdalen: The</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Alſo of Q Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</note> 
                  <hi>Queene commaunded me to ſignify to your La. that she is perſwaded she fareth much the better for your prayers, and therefore deſireth you, euer hereafter to be mindfull of her in your prayers.</hi> What eſteeme the Kings Councell had of her, appeareth by the forerecited letters. And the worſt that in their iudgement any Proteſtants, though her peeuiſh enemies, ſayd of her after her death, was that which doubtles was her greateſt honour, to wit, that ſhe was an earneſt Papiſt. I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude theſe teſtimonies with the iudgement of a certaine worthy Catholike, who albeit in the life of the La. <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a worthy Catholike</note> he ſeemed litle to fauour her, yet ſhe being dead he doubted not to ſay, <hi>That she left nor her like in all England.</hi> And truly of her we may vſe thoſe words of S. <hi>Augustine</hi> touching his Mother S. <hi>Monica: Whoſoeuer of thy ſeruants</hi> (O God) <hi>did know her, did in her much praiſe, honour, and loue thee, becauſe they perceiued thy preſence in her hart, the fruits of her holy conuerſation testifying the ſame. She was the wife of one husband,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Confeſſ. l.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>sherendred mutuall affection to her parents, she gouerned her houſe piouſly, she had her reputation in good workes, she gaue her children good education; as often as she ſaw them stray from thee, ſo often did she beare them anew.</hi> And all which things to be moſt true in this pious woman, all that knew her, will teſtifie with me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>THE CONCLVSION.</head>
               <p>BVt now <hi>Magdalens</hi> box is broken, and the houſe is filled with the odour of her oyntment; now the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of <hi>Gedeon</hi> is broken, and the light appeareth which darkeneth the ſight of the <hi>Madianites;</hi> now the body of our <hi>Magdalen</hi> is diſſolued, and her moſt rare and fragrant vertues dilate themſelues more clearly, and more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly. <hi>England</hi> may lament, that it hath loſt ſuch a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of Fayth, ſo worthy an ornament of Religion, ſuch a rare example of vertues. Nay it may rather reioyce, that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:183906:29"/> once it had, or rather hath ſuch a one. And certainly the La. <hi>Magdalen</hi> may reioyce, that ſhe hath found the thing ſo long, and ſo much deſired, that hauing left the world, ſhe is more abſolutely ioyned to almighty God. A happy <note place="margin">The La. Mag. hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the world.</note> woman (no doubt) touching the world; in that ſhe was of noble birth, married to a man of worthy fame and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, for a long time enoyed wealth, honour, proſperous health and fortune, long life &amp; worthy iſſue. Happy tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching her body; to whome God had giuen a ſound, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, and healthfull a body. Happy touching her ſoule, <note place="margin">Touching her body.</note> being endued with a moſt piercing wit, an excellent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, a profound iudgment, a ſtout and manly courage. But moſt happy towards God, who had giuen her ſo much grace, as to make vſe of her birth, honour, mariage, <note place="margin">Touching her ſoule.</note> wealth, beauty, iſſue, and finally of all the guifts &amp; graces of her body and ſoule, to the glory of God, &amp; her eternall felicity. If then (as the ſcripture teſtifyeth) they are Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">Moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God.</note> who dye in our Lord; how bleſſed ſhall we eſteeme this woman, who not only dyed, but alſo liued in our Lord; and not for a ſhort tyme, but all her lyfe; and that not indifferently, but moſt piouſly and religiouſly; and that in the land of <hi>Hus,</hi> where is the houre and power of darkenes, where piety is ſharply impugned, and freedome giuen to vice. Reſt now therfore, O <hi>Magdalen,</hi> from thy labours, from thy frequent faſtes, and dayly deuotions, and from thy other exerciſes of piety; reſt from the impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable <note place="margin">The La. Magd. dieth the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the tranſlatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of S. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica.</note> hatred, curſes, accuſations, and inquiſitions of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes: For thy workes of mercy, piety, chaſtity, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, fayth, hope, and charity do follow thee. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this pious widdow was tranſlated (as I hope) to a better lyfe, the day before the tranſlation of that moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly widdow <hi>S. Monica,</hi> to whome ſhe may be reſembled, I will conclude my writing of her, with the ſame wordes which <hi>S. Augustin</hi> concluded his, of his Mother <hi>S. Monica:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Confeſſ. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 11</note> which is thus: <hi>Albeyt being reuiued in Chriſt, her flesh not yet diſſolued, she liued ſo, as thy name</hi> (O God) <hi>may be prayſed in her fayth and conuerſation, yet dare I not ſay, that from the tyme thou</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:183906:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>diddest reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> are her by baptiſme, no word proceeded from her mouth, against thy precept, and woe to the laudable lyfe of men, if, thy mercy remoued, thou diſcuſſe the ſame. Therfore, O God of my hart, forge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>g a litle her good actes, for which I ioyfully giue that thankes, I no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> implore thee for the ſinnes of my</hi> (Lady;) <hi>heare me by the cure of our wounds, which hung on the Croſse, and ſitting at thy right hand mediateth for vs. She deſired memory should be made of her at thy Altar, where she aſsiſted without one dayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſsion, where she knew that holy oblation to be diſpenced wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the debt wherto we were ſubiect was cancelled, to which Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our redemption thy handmayd eyed her ſoule by the bond of fayth. And inſpire. O my Lord God, inſpire thy ſeruants my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, thy children my mayſters, that as often as they shall read this, they be mindfull at thy Altar, of</hi> (the Lady Magdalen) <hi>thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, with</hi> (Antony) <hi>ſometyme her husband.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>Of the day, place of birth, death, and buryall of the La. MAGDALEN Viſcounteſſe MONTAGVE.</p>
               <l>
                  <hi>The twentith day of</hi> Ianuary, <hi>firſt vitall breath her gaue;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The eight of</hi> Aprill <hi>stopt it quite, &amp; brought her to her graue:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Naward <hi>life did firſt affoard, which</hi> Battell <hi>tooke away;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And</hi> Midhurſt <hi>yeldeth to her Corps reſt, till the Iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t day.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:183906:30"/>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:183906:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:183906:31"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
